每天花幾分鍾思考死亡被認為是有用的、有啟發性的和治療性的。
It is considered useful and enlightening and therapeutic to think about death for a few minutes a day.
我對我的身體殘骸到底發生了什麼，一點也不感興趣。
What actually happens to my physical remains is of zero interest to me.
我不想讓任何人看到我的身體，我不想讓任何人…我不想要派對。
I don't want anybody seeing my body, I don't want anybody... I don't want a party.
“報道死了。”
"Reported dead."
除非它能給……帶來娛樂價值。我的意思是，以一種反常或顛覆的方式。
Unless it could provide entertainment value to... I mean, in a perverse or subversive way, you know.
我是說，如果你能把我扔進削木機和平底船…把我送到哈羅德，在高峰時段，那就太棒了。
I mean, if you could throw me into a wood chipper and punt... You know, spray me into harrods, you know, at, uh, you know, middle of the rush hour, that would be pretty epic.
我不介意被人以那種方式記住。
I wouldn't mind being remembered in that way.
1 2 3 4 5 6
□ One, two, three, four, five, six □
路鳥，路鳥
□ roadrunner, roadrunner □
□每小時加速□
□ going faster miles an hour □
□要開車經過□的商店
□ gonna drive past the stop & shop □
□對著□的收音機
□ with the radio on □
□我愛上了馬薩諸塞□
□ I'm in love with Massachusetts □
外面冷時的霓虹燈
□ and the neon when it's cold outside □
和高速公路在深夜
□ and the highway when it's late at night □
□把收音機對准了□
□ got the radio on □
□我就像一個跑路者……□
□ I'm like the roadrunner... □
我他媽在這干什麼?
What the fuck am I doing here?
我要解釋一下。
I shall explain.
前一分鍾我還站在油炸鍋旁，下一分鍾，我就在撒哈拉沙漠上看日落了。
One minute I was standing next to a deep fryer, and the next, I was watching the sun set over the Sahara.
□我愛上了現代的月光……□
□ I'm in love with modern moonlight... □
我意識到一件事直接導致了另一件事。
I realized that one thing led directly to the other.
如果我沒有做一份沒有前途的洗碗工作，我就不會成為一名廚師。
Had I not taken a dead-end dishwashing job, I would not have become a cook.
如果我沒有成為一名廚師，我永遠也不會成為一名廚師。
Had I not become a cook, I would never have become a chef.
如果我沒有成為一名廚師，我就不會把事情搞得這麼糟糕。
Had I not become a chef, I never would've been able to fuck up so spectacularly.
如果我不知道搞砸是什麼感覺，我寫的那本令人討厭但非常成功的回憶錄就不會有現在一半的有趣。
Had I not known what it was like to really fuck up, that obnoxious but wildly successful memoir I wrote wouldn't have been half as interesting.
我說走鵑一次，走鵑兩次
□ And I say roadrunner once, roadrunner twice □
我愛上了搖滾
□ I'm in love with rock and roll □
我整晚都在外面
□ and I'll be out all night □
□roadrunner，沒錯…□
□ roadrunner, that's right... □
我不會在這裡告訴你該如何生活。
And I'm not gonna tell you here how to live your life.
我只是想說，我很幸運。
I'm just saying, I guess, that I got very lucky.
□對□廣播
□ Radio on □
-我用對講機聽到了
- □ I got the am □ - □ radio on □
□得到了車，得到了車
□ got the car, got the am □
□對□廣播
□ radio on □
得到了am的聲音
□ got the am sound □
-□用對講機對著□
- □ got the □ - □ radio on □
得到了搖滾的現代霓虹燈聲
□ got the rockin' modern neon sound □
□對□廣播
□ radio on □
我從馬薩諸塞州買了輛車
□ I got the car from Massachusetts □
-□用對講機對著□
- □ got the □ - □ radio on □
我得到了馬薩諸塞的力量
□ I got the power of Massachusetts □
□當深夜□
□ when it's late at night □
正確□□
□ right □
□再見。□
□ bye-bye. □
反正你也會發現的，所以先說點實話。
You're probably gonna find out about it anyway, so here's a little preemptive truth telling.
沒有幸福的結局。
There's no happy ending.
他自殺了，該死的混蛋。
He committed suicide, the fucking asshole.
你要怎麼做?
How are you gonna make this?
它是……這是要……我的意思是……當然，你想說什麼，這就是八卦的來源，這就是……但這並不是你真正想做的。
Is it... is this gonna... I mean... Of course what you want to talk about, that's kind of where the gossip goes, that's kind of... But it's not really what you want to make.
不，我想拍一部關於他為什麼會是這樣的電影。
No, I want to make a film about why he was... who he was.
你知道的。
You know.
我不知道。我就是為此而來的。
I don't know. That's why I'm here.
你明白我的意思嗎?
Do you know what I mean?
我就是為此而來的。
That's why I'm here.
嗨。我是萊斯·哈勒斯的托尼，地址是公園大道南411號，請在周一送貨。
Hi. This is Tony at les halles, 411 park Avenue south, for delivery Monday please.
我要一根西班牙洋蔥，一根松的胡蘿卜，兩根沒去皮的蔥，一箱冷凍蠶豆和一箱普羅旺斯米酒。
I need one Spanish onion, one loose carrot, two shallot unpeeled, one case frozen fava bean and one case miel de provence.
要做的。謝謝你！
That'll do it. Thank you.
我的魚呢?
Where is my fucking fish?
我永遠不會遲到。
I would never be late.
我的廚師從不遲到。
My cooks would never be late.
賣魚的怎麼能遲到?
How can the fish guy be late?
所以廚師都是酒鬼。
It's why all chefs are drunks.
因為我們不明白為什麼這個世界不像我們的廚房那樣運轉。
It's because we don't understand why the world doesn't work like our kitchens.
-等等-如果你們是匈奴人…這就是baba ghanoush。這是……我是說，這不是一個很好的展示-我了解托尼。——酷。
- Oh, hold on. - If you guys are hun... It's just baba ghanoush. It's... I mean, it's not a very nice display, - I know Tony. - Cool.
謝謝你,寶貝。
Thanks, baby.
-你想要點什麼?——嗯…——蘋果汁。——蘋果汁?蘋果汁嗎?
- What would you like? - Um... - Apple juice. - Apple juice? Apple juice?
或蔓越莓。我也不在乎只要我們有更多的。
Or cranberry. I don't care. Whatever we have more of.
幸福是一個新鮮的包。
Happiness is a fresh pack.
早上第一件事。
First thing in the morning.
我是說，在我刷牙之前。
I mean, before I brush my teeth.
我是說，我從床上爬起來，點了根煙，跌跌撞撞地走進這間屋子，然後，我馬上開始寫作。
I mean, I roll out of bed, light a cigarette, stumble into this room, and, uh, I start, uh, I start writing immediately.
我總是用語言來擺脫困境。
I always use language to get out of trouble.
你知道，我在很小的時候就發現，如果我能讓班裡的每個人笑，那就是力量。
You know, I found at an early age, if I made everybody in the class laugh, that was power.
我來自一個有很多書的家庭。
I came from a household with a lot of books.
事實上，我記得我讀的第一本書是一本叫《約翰尼為什麼不識字》的書，是我從我母親那裡偷來的。
In fact, the first book I remember reading was a book called why Johnny can't read, which I stole from my mother.
她預料到我會有閱讀困難，因為我已經表現出反社會的傾向。
She was anticipating that I would have a difficulty reading because I was already exhibiting antisocial tendencies.
我拿了這本書，基本上是在幼兒園的時候自學的。
Uh, I pinched the book and, uh, basically taught myself to read, uh, by kindergarten.
然後，你知道，我早期的偶像是音樂家和作家。
And then, you know, my early heroes were, uh, musicians and-and writers.
不管你的冒險有多反社會，你都可以通過寫一些美好的東西讓它們變得合法，這個想法很早就在我腦海中形成了。
The idea that you could have adventures, no matter how antisocial, and then make them somehow legitimate by writing something beautiful about them, that concept took an early hold on me.
在93年之前，我對任何事情都不夠認真，沒有真正寫過任何東西。
I wasn't serious enough about anything to actually do any writing until '93.
但是，你知道，當我有機會的時候，我做了，而且，你知道，一直做。
But, you know, when I was given the opportunity, I did it, and, you know, kept doing it.
坦白說，這整件事讓我感到恐懼。
The whole business fills me with terror, frankly.
嘿。
Hey.
你好嗎，伙計?
How are you doing, man?
-你們現在已經認識了——是的。
- You guys know each other by now. - Yes.
讓我看看羅科結束了沒有。
Let me see if Rocco's over.
托尼拿著大刀子是怎麼回事?
What was it about Tony with big knives?
它們從來都不夠鋒利。
They were never sharp enough.
你知道,他是……他總是……他來過感恩節的時候，我本來打算切火雞的，然後他就接手了。
You know, he's... He'd just always... When he came over for Thanksgiving, uh, I was gonna carve the Turkey, and then he took over.
他對我很不客氣，說我沒好好照顧我的刀。
He was very short with me about how I wasn't taking care of my knives.
-嗨。-你剛出生的時候托尼見過你。
- Hey. - Tony saw you when you were just born.
還記得嗎?
Remember that?
我和托尼一直以作家的身份交往。
My relationship with Tony has always been as a writer.
他從一開始就是一個很有影響力的作家。
He was such a powerful writer right from the start.
他第一次到東京出差。
He was on business in Tokyo for the first time.
他給我寫了一系列郵件。
And he was writing me a series of emails.
他回到了自己的房間，然後又爆發了一次。
He was back in his room, and he-he did one of those bursts.
"時差讓我睡不著，"所以我睡得晚，露得早，"一直在黑暗的街道上瞎晃。
"The jet lag wouldn't let me sleep, "so I crashed late and Rose early, "plunging blindly down dark streets at all hours.
“街上擠滿了行人，”人們四處閒逛，閃爍著霓虹燈，“揮舞著橫幅，還有更多尖叫的標語，”穿著西裝和漆皮鞋的滿臉疙瘩的年輕人
"The streets were unbelievably dense with pedestrians, "people hanging around, flashing neon, "flapping banners, more screaming signs, "pimpy-looking young men in suits and patent leather shoes
"周圍都是金發亞洲女人"穿著長筒靴和迷你裙。
"surrounded by dye-blonde Asian women "in thigh-high boots and micro-mini skirts.
沒有人，我是說沒有人，會直視我的眼睛。
"No one, and I mean no one, would meet my eye "with a direct gaze.
"我是一個安靜的美國人，一個丑陋的美國人，"一個饑餓的幽靈，不停地尋找接下來發生的一切"
"I was the quiet American, the ugly American, "the hungry ghost, searching and searching for whatever came next."
我很喜歡。我很喜歡，我的妻子凱倫(Karen)是一位圖書出版商，當時她正在客廳裡給孩子喂奶。
I loved it. I loved it, and my wife Karen, who was a book publisher, was in the living room breastfeeding the baby.
我把郵件打印出來，然後說"凱倫，你得讀讀這個"
I printed out the email and I went, "Karen, you have to read this."
我可以罵人嗎?
Am I allowed to curse?
當他們談論這個的時候，有人詛咒嗎?
Does anybody curse when they talk about this?
我讀了之後就說"太他媽棒了"
I read it and I just went, "that is fucking awesome."
我說"好吧"我會給他一個條件"基本上他他媽是無法拒絕的"
I was like, "okay", I'm gonna make him an offer "basically he can't fucking refuse."
他回來了，然後我們坐下。
He came back and then we sat down.
我說，“喬爾告訴我，你知道，你有很多故事。”
I said, "so Joel tells me, you know, you have a lot of stories."
他說，“我有很多故事。
And he goes, "I have so many stories.
我很興奮地告訴他們。”
I'm so excited to tell them."
他說:“我已經給它起了個名字。”
He said, "I already have a title for it."
我說:“標題是什麼?”
I said, "what's the title?"
他說:“廚房機密。”
And he said, "kitchen confidential."
我說:“我喜歡。讓我們做它。”
And I said, "I love it. Let's do it."
你覺得托尼·波登怎麼樣?
What do you think about Tony bourdain anyway?
你覺得那個人怎麼樣?
Yeah, what do you think about that guy?
他很酷。嗯?
He's cool. Huh?
就像"你會寫這本書嗎"
It was like, "will you write this book?"
“是的。”
"Yes."
“你能在八個月內寫完嗎?”
"Can you write it in eight months?"
“你說得對，我會的。”
"You're damn right I will."
你應該和托尼的經紀人金·威瑟斯彭談談。
You know, you should talk to Tony's agent, Kim Witherspoon.
我不認為托尼害怕失敗，那是天生的。
I don't think Tony was afraid of failure, and that was hard-wired.
他是那種會想，“你知道，搞什麼鬼?”
He was the kind of person who thought, "well, you know, what the fuck?
讓我們試試看，看看結果如何。”
Let's just try it and see how it turns out."
從事廚師工作28年的安東尼•波登在一本名為《廚房機密》的新書中透露了一些令人驚訝和不安的商業秘密。
Anthony bourdain, who has worked as a chef for 28 years, reveals some surprising and disturbing trade secrets in a new book called kitchen confidential.
廚師安東尼講述了餐館裡面包的真相，你點肉的時候應該怎麼做，還有魚會讓你生病的真相。
Chef Anthony says the truth about bread in a restaurant, how you should prepare your meat when you order it, and also the truth about fish could make you sick.
我上一家餐廳關門後心情很不好我覺得沒有理由不告訴你這個我既喜歡又有復雜感情的生意。
I was in a cranky mood after my last restaurant closed and, uh, felt no reason not to tell the truth about a business I both love and, uh, have mixed emotions about.
《廚房機密》是托尼在廚房生活的回憶錄，以及他和廚師們的鹹味冒險經歷。
Kitchen confidential is a memoir of Tony's life in the kitchen and the salty adventures that he had with his cooks.
這有點無法無天。
It was kind of lawless.
就像托尼常說的，很多東西都破碎了。
You know, a lot was broken, as Tony used to say.
波登先生是les halles餐廳的行政主廚。
Mr. Bourdain is the executive chef at les halles.
他在很小的時候就取得了成功並染上了完全的海洛因癮。
He found success and a full-blown heroin habit at an early age.
我曾經吸毒成癮，吸食可卡因，但到了88年，我已經改過自新了。
I had a dope problem, a cocaine problem, but by '88, I pretty much cleaned up my act.
每個廚師都需要的膳食補充劑。
The dietary supplement that every chef needs.
我一天要吃十顆左右。
I take around ten of these a day.
這是阿司匹林和泰諾的混合物。
It's an aspirin/tylenol mix.
叫他們脆。
Call 'em crunchies.
讓我帶你來個夢幻之旅看看我們今晚的菜單。
Let me take you on a notional joyride through our menu tonight.
我們有酸模醬烤鮭魚。
We have grilled salmon with sorrel sauce.
小牛肉腎髒。
Veal kidneys.
順便說一句，這些腎真的很好。
These kidneys are really good, by the way.
喜歡水上運動的人會發現有很多可以喜歡的。
Those of you into water sports will find much to love.
我記得第一次見到他時，我就在想，哇，你又高又帥又風趣。
From the first time I met him, I remember thinking, "oh, wow, you're, like, tall and handsome and funny.
“但你有點像個大書呆子。
"But you're kind of a big nerd.
“你對所有事情都很厭煩，而且有點尷尬，”
"You're nerding out on everything, and you're a little awkward,"
我喜歡他這一點
and I love that about him.
"在les halles，生活一如既往，"每天都有同樣的工作人員准時到場。
"At les halles, life goes on as always, "the same crew showing up on time every day.
艾迪，卡洛斯和奧馬爾，伊西多羅和天使。
"Eddy, "Carlos and Omar, isidoro and angel.
“他們仍然和我在一起，我希望他們繼續和我在一起。
"They're still with me, and I hope they stay with me.
然而，當我的老板們讀到這篇文章時，“如果他們不能馬上給我寫信，他們就真的會證明自己是藝術的贊助人。”
"My bosses, however, when they read this, "will really prove themselves patrons of the arts if they don't can me right away."
所以你沒有解雇他?
So you didn't fire him?
我沒有解雇他。
I didn't fire him.
我不知道有這麼寫。
I didn't know it was being written.
我不知道這本書會出版。
I didn't know it was going to be published.
有一天，我到了餐廳，就問"發生什麼事了"
Uh, one day, I arrived at the restaurant, and I just said, "what happened?"
你他媽的開什麼玩笑。
You're fucking kidding me.
今天有人告訴我，我猜，這個月12號，這本書會在《泰晤士報》暢銷書排行榜上排名第七。
I was told today that on, I guess, the 12th of this month, it'll be number seven on the times best seller list.
因為是在20碼，不是嗎?然後,呃…我是說，我接到了祝賀電話，他們說我有本暢銷書。
'Cause it was on 20, wasn't it? And then, uh... I mean, I'm getting congratulatory calls, and they're telling me I have a best seller.
真的，這很可怕。
Uh, really, it's scary.
不,這是令人興奮的。這是美妙的。
No, it's exciting. It's wonderful.
是的,我只是……我對門外發生的任何事都持懷疑態度。
Yeah, I just... Anything that happens beyond that door I'm suspicious of.
他總是拖欠房租，總是拖欠，你知道的，他總是過著一份又一份的生活，就像在高壓鍋裡一樣。
He was always behind in the rent, always behind his, you know, payments and-and-and living from paycheck to paycheck, like in a pressure cooker.
所以當有機會時，他已經准備好了。
So when there was this opportunity, he-he was ready.
在我43歲的時候，"我真的以為我所有偉大的冒險經歷都已經結束了，"節目的娛樂和刺激部分早就結束了"
"By the time I was 43, "I really thought that I had had all my great adventures, "that the entertainment and excitement segment of the program was long over."
——怎麼了?——謝謝。
- What's up? - Thank you.
這是很酷。
That was cool.
"我舒適地安頓在安全的住所裡和妻子在一起她仍然覺得我偶爾很有趣"
"I was comfortably ensconced "in secure digs with a wife who still remarkably found me to be amusing on occasion."
什麼?你在干什麼?你接受采訪嗎?
What? What are you doing? You're giving interviews?
你在干什麼。
What are you... you media hoe.
"我有一份熱愛的工作"在一家成功的餐廳，而且我還活著，天哪。
"I had a job I loved in "a successful restaurant, and I was alive, for Christ's sakes.
我還在。”
I was still around."
我在家不做飯。
I don't cook at home.
我只是…我太…我很樂意告訴你，你知道的，我回家會給我妻子做美味的小點心。
I-I just... I'm too, uh... I would love to tell you, you know, I go home and-and cook fabulous, uh, little snackies for-for my wife.
如果我告訴你那是在撒謊。
I would be lying if I told you that.
更像是"親愛的，喊中文"
It's more like, "honey, call out for Chinese."
"事實證明，有很多種方式"來表達"去舔我的雞巴"
"There are, it turns out, a million ways "to say 'suck my dick.'
就像所有偉大的表演一樣，“關鍵在於時機、語氣和表達方式，有點像烹飪。”
"and like all great performances, "it's about timing, tone and delivery, kind of like cooking."
謝謝。
Thanks.
你知道嗎，電視上的廚師都很可愛。
You know, all the TV chefs are so cuddly and adorable, you know.
也許我就是解藥之類的。
Maybe I'm the... sort of like the antidote or something.
你知道嗎?我不知道。
You know? I don't know.
對我來說，這發生在一夜之間。
For me, it happened overnight.
我是說，前一分鍾，我還是一家餐廳的廚師，不是一家特別棒的餐廳，下一分鍾，我就成了一名作家，一夜之間就成名了。
I mean, one minute, I was a cook at a restaurant, and not a particularly great one, and the next, I was an author, and it was literally overnight.
它從天而降。
It fell in my lap.
現在請到安東尼·波登，《廚房機密》的作者。
Joining me now is Anthony bourdain, author of kitchen confidential.
安東尼……廚師安東尼……這是安東尼。
Anthony bourdain... Chef Anthony bourdain... Here's Anthony bourdain.
你對這些人有什麼看法，比如emeril lagasse和那些在食品網絡上的人?——哇。
What-what do you think about these guys - like emeril lagasse and those guys on the food network? - Wow.
你是在讓我，在電視上踢聖誕老人的襠部。
Y-You're asking me to, you know, kick Santa claus in the crotch on television.
我的意思是……我的生活變得越來越可笑。
I mean... My life gets more and more ridiculous.
顯然，布拉德·皮特會在電影裡扮演我。
Apparently, Brad Pitt will be playing me in a movie.
是啊，猜猜明天有什麼。
Yeah, guess what's, uh, tomorrow.
——明天是什麼?——奧普拉。
- What's tomorrow? - Oprah.
不!你是在跟我開玩笑吧!
No! You're kidding me!
這位是安東尼·波登。
This is Anthony bourdain.
他的《廚房機密》是《紐約時報》的暢銷書。
His book kitchen confidential is a New York times best seller.
我生來就會做飯。
I was born to cook.
我喜歡滿足人們的欲望。
I loved satisfying people's appetites.
接下來，我要和艾梅裡爾一起跳藍巴達舞。
Next, I'll be, uh, doing the lambada with emeril.
砰!只是有點……
Bam! Just a little...
我討厭我自己。
I'd hate myself.
謝謝。
Thanks.
哦!哇!
Oh! Whoa!
——啊。-托尼·波登太棒了!
- Ah. - Tony bourdain rocks!
怎麼了,伙計?一切都好嗎?
What's up, man? Everything good?
-生活很美好。——是的,是的。
- Life is good. - Yes, yes.
我們在慶祝托尼的書。
We're celebrating Tony's book.
-過來，姑娘。在這裡。-嗨。
- Come here, girl. Get in here. - Hi.
-你好嗎?——好。
- How you doing? - Good.
-我是托尼。-嗨。
- This is Tony. - Hi.
-你好。——哦,祝賀你。
- Howdy. - Oh, congratulations.
我們玩得很開心。
We're having a good time.
哦，哦，下一個?
Oh, oh, the next one?
不，下一個，我要做一個廚師之旅。
No, the next one, I'm doing something called a cook's tour.
基本上，我要環游世界，吃異國風味的食物，去遠東、非洲和南美冒險……有一群人在追我
Basically, I'm gonna travel around the world, eating exotic food and having adventures in the far east and Africa and South America... With a crew chasing me.
嘿，約翰，過來。
Hey, John, come here.
我那15分鍾的"成名"經歷結束後，就算不能松一口氣，我也會覺得很舒服。
You know, my 15 minutes of quote, unquote "fame," uh, you know, when that's over, uh, I will be perfectly comfortable with that, if not relieved.
我想我現在甚至松了一口氣。
I think even relieved at this point.
當我第一次見到他時，他對廚房機密已經引起了轟動。
When I met him for the first time, he had made a splash with kitchen confidential.
我聽說他簽了一份合同，要寫第二本書《廚師之旅》，於是我給他打了電話。
I had read that he had a contract to write a second book called a cook's tour, and I called him.
——是嗎?-我說"我是制作人"——做好事。
- Yes? - And I said, - "hey, I'm a producer." - Doing good.
“你有沒有想過把庫克的巡演拍成系列節目?”
"Would you ever even consider making cook's tour into a series?"
然後他，你知道的，他就像，你知道的，"隨便吧"
And he, you know, he was like, you know, "yeah, uh, whatever."
——你知道嗎?“當然。”——確定。
- You know? "Sure." - Sure.
他對在電視上做任何事情都感到非常困惑。
He was very nonplussed about the whole idea of doing anything in television.
這不是他所想的。
It was not what was on his mind.
再見。
Bye-bye.
一周半後，我和克裡斯·柯林斯去了萊斯·哈勒斯。
A week and a half later, Chris Collins and I went up to les halles.
我們找到了托尼，和他一起拍了個樣帶，還和他聊了聊。
We found Tony, shot a demo with him and had a conversation with him.
很明顯，他從未出過國。
And it became immediately clear he had never traveled.
莉迪亞和我是比托尼·波登更偉大的世界旅行者。
Lydia and I were far greater world travelers than Tony bourdain.
他的旅行在他的腦海裡。
His travels were in his head.
我想去遙遠的異國情調的地方那裡有棕櫚樹那裡穿著軍裝的青少年拿著機關槍。
You know, I want to go to faraway exotic places with palm trees and where teenagers in army uniforms carry machine guns.
我從小就看《深紅海盜》
Growing up as a kid, you know, I watched the crimson pirate.
你知道的，所有的海盜和壞人都有偉大的冒險。
You know, all pirates and bad guys having great adventures.
托尼的世界觀來自書籍和電影。
Tony's view of the world emanated from books and from films.
他幾乎像百科全書一樣，能抓住所有這些參考文獻。
Almost in an encyclopedic way, he could grab all these references.
我想他很高興踏上這段旅程，看看現實是否與想象相符。
And I think he was excited to go on this journey to see if the reality actually matched the imagination.
2000年12月我們出發的那一刻，是不可磨滅的。
That moment when we set out in December of 2000, it's indelible.
我們的第一次旅行，持續了六個星期。
Our first journey was, um, for six weeks.
記住，我們只花了一次……有一天和托尼一起走到那一刻。
And remember, we'd only spent one... One day with Tony leading up to that moment.
托尼的形象，我的意思是，我認為，在那一刻，是一個非常不確定將要發生什麼事的人。
The image of Tony, I mean, it was, I think, a guy who, at that moment, was very unsure of what was about to happen.
這種方式。
This way.
你知道，我在一個艱難的行業裡看著一個奇怪的，呃，不可預測的未來，我不完全熟悉規則，當我熟悉它們時，我……
You know, I'm looking at a strange and, uh, unpredictable future in a tough business with rules that I'm not com-completely familiar with, and when I become familiar with them, I...
你知道，我不知道我是不是那麼喜歡他們。
You know, I don't know whether I like them that much.
我們一起上路了，就我們三個。
We hit the road together, just the three of us.
莉迪亞和我剛剛結婚。
Lydia and I had just gotten married.
然後我們有了托尼，一個我們幾乎不認識的人。
And then we had Tony, a guy who we barely knew.
所以就像三個白癡想要弄清彼此。
So it was like three idiots trying to figure each other out.
首先是日本。
The first shoot was Japan.
我們都不知道自己在做什麼。
Like, we didn't know what we were doing.
他肯定不知道自己在做什麼。
He definitely didn't know what he was doing.
托尼立刻變得不舒服和尷尬。
And Tony immediately became uncomfortable and awkward.
我們很快就會發現。
What we would find out very quickly is.
托尼其實是個很害羞的人。
Tony was actually a very shy human being.
為了讓他進行眼神交流或互動，這不是他的自然狀態。
And to get him to make eye contact or to interact, it wasn't his natural state.
你知道，和托尼·波登在一起的生活並不像人們說的那麼美好。
You know, life on the road with Tony bourdain just isn't all it's cracked up to be.
你懂我的意思嗎?
You know what I mean?
這人有時真讓人討厭。
The man can be a royal pain in the ass sometimes.
事實上，我嘴唇上現在長了個唇皰疹，這是壓力造成的，因為托尼缺乏溝通而產生的壓力。
In fact, I got this cold sore on my lip now, and it's due to stress, stress over Tony's lack of communication.
更糟糕的是，我們在日本的時候被引導到一個場景裡面有很多，有點正式的東西，你知道，所有這些因素都導致了他的安靜，
That, compounded by the fact that we were in Japan being sort of led into scenes where there was a lot of, kind of, formality involved, you know, all of those factored into him being quiet,
這是最糟糕的事了。
which was like the worst possible thing.
嗯。哦,哇。
Mmm. Oh, wow.
壯觀。
Spectacular.
我的意思是，克裡斯和我回到酒店，基本上看著對方，然後說……我們受騙的。
I mean, Chris and I went back to the hotel and basically looked at each other and said like... We're fucked.
克裡斯,可以…克裡斯，給我和莉迪亞拍張照片，我們回來時，太陽在她身後，當我們走過黃色三角形標志時，我們指著山上的農捨。
Chris, can... Chris, take a picture of me and Lydia as we come back with the sun behind her, pointing up the mountain towards the farmhouse as we walk up past the yellow triangular sign.
謝謝你！
Thank you.
好吧。我們開始吧。
Okay. Here we go.
好吧。
Okay.
我是說，說實話，我不是一個人，因為很明顯有人在拍這個。
I mean, to be honest, I'm not totally alone, 'cause clearly somebody is shooting this.
我一直很喜歡沙漠的場景，“我一個人在沙漠裡。”
I always love those, like, desert scenes, "I'm alone in the desert."
是啊，但那是誰的腳印?
Yeah, but who else's footprints are those?
你知道，就是那種東西。但是看。
You know, one of those things. But-but look.
這很酷。
This is pretty cool.
走路的感覺真的很酷……好吧，我告訴你:我向前走比攝影師向後走有趣多了，我敢肯定。
And it does feel pretty cool to be walking... Well, I'll tell you this: I'm having a lot more fun walking forward than the cameraperson is walking backwards, I'm sure.
那是呻吟聲嗎?
Was that a groan?
是的,它是。
Yes, it was.
我們從日本去了越南。
We went from Japan to Vietnam.
從那時起，事情開始變得不同了。
That's when things started to kick in to a different gear.
我的好朋友菲利普·拉胡尼，昨晚出乎意料地來了。
My good friend Phillipe lajaunie, uh, pulled in, uh, semi-unexpectedly last night.
我們准備好去冒險了嗎?
We're ready for, uh, ready for our adventure?
我第一次和他們一起去越南，他玩得很開心，也不那麼憤世嫉俗了。
I joined them on that first trip in Vietnam, and he was enjoying himself and being less cynical.
嘿。
Hey.
漂浮的星巴克在這裡。
Floating Starbucks over here.
我要雙份拿鐵，請給我摩卡奇諾。
I'll have a double latte, uh, mochaccino please.
哦,太好了。
Oh, that's great.
把星巴克踢得屁滾尿流。
Kicks the shit out of Starbucks.
“我愛越南。
"I love Vietnam.
也許這是一種信息素的作用，就像你第一次遇見"你生命中的真愛"
"Maybe it's a pheromonic thing, like when you meet "the love of your life for the first time.
她只是，不知怎麼的，"聞起來感覺很好。
"She just, somehow, "inexplicably smells and feels right.
“你感覺到，只要有機會，她就是你想要共度余生的女人。”
"You sense that, given the opportunity, this is the woman you want to spend the rest of your life with."
我們都希望能在越南呆上一段時間，也許永遠呆在那裡。
We had common desire to spend time in Vietnam, maybe forever.
那是我們的秘密紐帶。
That was our secret bond.
當然，電影《天啟》是他一生中排名前三的電影之一，因為它結合了很多東西:
And of course, the movie apocalypse now was one of his top three movies in his life, uh, because it combined so many things:
越戰，戰爭還有那本書，黑暗的心髒。
Vietnam and the war and-and the book, the heart of darkness.
我們剛開始做這些自我放縱的電影參考，然後我突然意識到，“等一下。
We just started doing all of this self-indulgent film references, and I suddenly realized, "wait a minute.
拍電影可能會很有趣。”
This-this filmmaking thing can be fun."
□啊!□
□ Ah! □
你知道，這是一個大蠟筆盒。
You know, it's a big crayon box.
我們可以享受這個。
We can actually enjoy this.
我為什麼在這裡?我瘋了嗎?
Why am I here? Am I insane?
他以前常說"別讓我上電視"
You know, he used to say, "don't ever let me do TV.
事情就像，如果我要上電視，就斃了我。”
Thing is like, if I ever do TV, shoot me."
你知道，剛開始的時候，感覺很糟糕。
And, you know, at first, it was awful.
廚師是從哪裡來的?
Where do cooks come from?
這個問題的答案和其他問題的答案都在後面。
The answer to this and other questions to follow.
然後很快地……他是個好學生，他非常聰明……他好像發現了。
And then very quickly... He's such a good student, he's so freaking smart... He, like, figured it out.
克裡斯，莉迪亞，我愛你們。
Chris, Lydia, I love you.
你知道的，對吧?
You know that, right?
但我要在曼谷待一晚，好嗎?
But I got one night in Bangkok here, okay?
我們在這裡躺了還不到24小時。
So not even 24 hours we're laying over here.
你想在24小時內演完一整部劇嗎?
You want to do a whole goddamn show in 24 hours?
很好。好吧?
Fine. Okay?
但是不要忘了屏蔽。
But... forget about blocking out.
沒有計劃，你最好快點。
No plan and you better be fast.
我會玩得很開心的。我們會滾。
I'm gonna have a good time. We're gonna roll.
如果你不懂，你就不懂。
And if you don't get it, you don't get it.
用我們的話說，就是在剪輯的時候抓住它。
Catch it in editing, as we like to say.
在那一刻開始成長的是這樣一種理解:“托尼，你不需要告訴我們一切。
What started to grow at that moment was this understanding, "Tony, you don't need to tell us everything.
“你需要經歷這些，並提出問題。
"You need to experience this and ask questions.
“這就是我們從這裡學到的東西。
"That's how we're all gonna learn from this place.
“你不是旅游指南。
"It's not you being a travel guide.
而是你對這種經歷持開放態度。”
It's you being open to this experience."
哦,耶穌。
Oh, Jesus.
看看這個。
Look at this.
看看這個東西。
Look at this thing.
看看到處都冒出來的魚卵。
Look at the roe just popping out everywhere.
只是在……哇!哇。
Just in... whoa! Whoa.
回來了。爸爸。
Come back. Come to papa.
如果有什麼菜是最完美的，那就是這道菜。
If there is any dish that comes closest to perfection, this is it, you know.
這簡直就是天堂之牆。
This is bumping up right up against the walls of heaven.
啊,男人。
Ah, man.
我們已經到達山頂了。
We've reached the mountaintop.
試著去想"我想要什麼"
And trying to think, you know, "what do I want?"
能買些能填補我靈魂空虛部分的東西當然不錯，但我什麼都想不出來。
It would be nice to buy something that will fulfill some hollow part of my soul, but I can't think of, you know, anything.
也許一輛車就可以了。我不知道。
Maybe a car will do it. I-I don't know.
我是說，該死，我的房租已經付了。
I mean, shit, my rent is paid.
僅這一點就很了不起。
That alone is spectacular.
我的意思是,我…我想過正常人的生活。
I mean, i-i... I'd like to live like a normal person.
那一直是我的想法，如果我有足夠的錢，我就能像正常人一樣生活。
That was always my thought, that-that if I get enough money, I'll be able to live like a normal person.
但我都不知道那是什麼了。
But I don't even know what that is anymore.
我當時看了廚房機密，給他打了電話。
I read kitchen confidential at that time, and I call him.
我邀請他和我共進午餐因為我想見見他。
And I invite him to have lunch with me because I want to meet the man.
然後他帶著一個電視攝制組出現了。
And he shows up with a-a TV crew.
我還以為這是頭獎呢。
I thought this was a jackpot.
這是我的偶像之一。
This was one of my idols.
我完全被嚇壞了。
I was just absolutely freaked out.
難以置信的復雜，精致，干淨，美麗，無可挑剔的呈現。
Incredibly sophisticated, refined, clean, beautiful, impeccably presented.
埃裡克做的食物就像是技藝的巔峰之作。
Eric's food is like the craft performed at its highest level.
當我見到他的時候，我不指望他……說得這麼清楚。
When I meet him, I don't expect him... To be so articulate.
而且他在餐桌上非常有禮貌。
And he has amazing good manners at the table.
我想在晚餐結束的時候，我們說我們應該再見面。
And I think at the end of the meal, we said we should meet again.
然後，嗯，我們就這麼做了。
And, um, and we did.
配鵝肝慕斯和…
Served with foie gras mousse and notes of...
我認為不是掙扎…我不知道“奮斗”這個詞是否恰當，但我面臨的挑戰是真實，保持真實，同時，做一個電視節目的主持人。
I think what was not a struggle... I don't know if "struggle" is the right word, but the challenge was to be real, stay real, and at the same time, be the host of a TV show.
你得稍微誇張一點。
You have to exaggerate a little bit.
這就像穿著貂皮內褲開勞斯萊斯一樣。
This is like driving a Rolls-Royce naked in mink underpants.
太過奢華了。
Just so over-the-top luxurious.
我認為人們在鏡頭前所經歷的人似乎有一種不可思議的能力，能夠與他遇到的任何人進行交流。
I think the person that people experienced on camera was someone who seemingly had this incredible ability to engage with anybody he came across.
這就像聯合國的詹姆斯·邦德，可以天鵝般進入場景。
It's like the UN-muscled James Bond who could kind of swan into scenes.
這是隨著時間的推移而形成的角色。
There was that persona that was created over time.
我在尋找極端的情感和經驗。
I am looking for extremes of emotion and experience.
我什麼都想嘗嘗。我會不惜一切。
I'll try anything. I'll risk everything.
我沒有什麼可失去的。
I have nothing to lose.
故事講的是一個廚師的旅行，講的是一個抽煙喝酒的人在世界各地大吃大喝的故事。
The story was a cook's tour was about a guy who smoke and drank and ate his way around the world.
這是真實的。
That was true.
其中一段是"他也會吃很奇怪的東西"
Part of the pitch was, "and he's gonna eat really weird shit, too."
讓我們做些下流的。
Let's-let's do the nasty.
他們似乎不在一起。
They don't seem to have their mise en place together.
當我做牛排薯條的時候，我把我的食物放在一起。
I have my mise en place together when I'm making steak frites.
在我看來，你知道，當你在做眼鏡蛇的時候，你知道的，你應該把你的操作材料擺出來。
It seems to me, you know, when you're making live cobra, you know, you should have your operating stuff laid out.
切菜板呢，刀呢?
You know, where's the cutting board, the knife?
剪刀嗎?
Scissors?
你知道，吃這些東西是為了攝像機，為了網絡，人們這樣做的所有原因。
You know, eating those kind of things was for camera, was for network, was for all the reasons people do that.
就像，你知道，有點淫蕩，就像他在吃活的，跳動的眼鏡蛇心髒。
It's like, you know, it's a little salacious, like he's eating a live, beating cobra heart.
干杯,朋友們。
Cheers, folks.
感覺強烈。
Feels strong.
它在下落的過程中也會抽動。
It kind of pumps on its way down, too.
我認為這個角色跟隨了他很多年，但隨著時間的推移，它消失了，變成了托尼。
And I think that persona followed him for a number of years, but over time, that burned off and it became Tony.
回到祖先的故鄉，也許我們會在途中發現一些東西。
Going back to the ancestral homeland, and maybe we'll discover some things along the way.
這是我父親和一個小朋友在法國吉倫德的一個牡蠣村。
So this is my father and a little friend in France in a little oyster village in the gironde.
這也是我最喜歡的照片之一。
This is one of my favorite pictures, also.
我弟弟和我在同一個地方。
Uh, my brother and I in the same spot.
小時候我們沒有經常旅行，因為我父母不富裕。
We didn't do a lot of travel when we were kids 'cause my parents were not rich.
我們確實去過法國幾次，因為我爸爸在那裡有親戚。
We did go to France a couple of times because my dad had relatives there.
我緊張。
I'm nervous.
誰會想到我們會做這麼愚蠢的事?
Whoever thought we'd do something this goofy?
這不是愚蠢的。
This isn't goofy.
當我們還是美國孩子的時候，我們真的很喜歡丁丁書，美國人說“丁丁”。
Our childhood as American kids, we really got into tintin books, which Americans say "tin-tin."
這是一本漫畫小說，講的是一個年輕的記者周游世界，最後經歷了各種奇妙的冒險。
This was a graphic novel about this young reporter who travels all around the world and ends up with all of these amazing adventures.
我認為在某種程度上，它實際上是托尼生活的靈感來源。
I think it was actually, in some ways, an inspiration for Tony's life.
這是一艘牡蠣船，和我第一次吃牡蠣的船很相似。
This is an oyster boat similar to the one on which I had my first oyster.
"我責怪我的第一個生蠔" "為我之後所做的一切"我追求刺激，為追求快樂而做的所有可怕的蠢事"
"I blame my first oyster "for everything I did after: My thrill-seeking, all my hideous screwups in pursuit of pleasure."
“我痛苦又憤怒。”
"I was miserable and angry."
該死的!我們小時候可沒吃過。
Damn! We didn't get those when we were kids.
——不,不。——他!
- No, no. - He-he!
我對“在我的家裡被愛和正常扼住了喉嚨”感到憤怒。
"I bridled bitterly at "the smothering chokehold of love and normalcy in my house.
“可以稱之為性格缺陷，藥物只是這種缺陷的一種表現。”
"Call it a character flaw, of which drugs were simply a manifestation."
——突出,下士!——最優秀的。
- Outstanding, corporal! - Most excellent.
“一個任性的‘操你媽’
"A petulant 'fuck you'
“獻給我的資產階級父母，他們犯下了不可饒恕的罪孽，愛我。”
"to my bourgeois parents, who'd committed the unpardonable sin of loving me."
-我真的很高興我們有機會這樣做。——我也是。
- I'm really glad we got a chance to do this. - Me, too.
我們現在長大了，更成熟了。
We're older and more mature now.
-是的。——好的。
- Yeah. - Okay.
我們再做一個。
Yeah, let's do another one.
-是的。——好的。
- Yeah. - Okay.
好吧，休息兩分鍾。
All right, um, take two.
“兩年前，飛行裡程對我來說毫無意義。
"Two years ago, frequent flyer miles meant nothing to me.
今天，所獲得的裡程是我可悲的裡程碑……”
Today, miles earned are the pathetic milestones of my..."
——頂部?-是的，從上面開始。
- Top? - Yeah, start at the top.
好了，第三次。
All right, take three.
我們會在開頭寫旁白。
We would write the voice-over in the beginning.
比如，我們需要我們所看到的背景。
Like, we need context for what we're seeing.
我們需要一些現場概要。
We need some summary of the scene.
"之後，我將在東南亞進行另一次巡訪"在這裡或那裡中途停留。
"Later, I'm on another swing through Southeast Asia "with layovers here and there.
“第一站,新加坡。
"First stop, Singapore.
和我的編輯ilangoh t一起吃個商務晚餐……”
A quick business dinner with my editor, ilangoh t..."
“Tanalaban”?“Tanadab……”“塔……”它是……不。
"Tanalaban"? "Tanadab..." "Tana..." Is it... no.
——Thanabalan。——Thanabalan。好吧。
- Thanabalan. - Thanabalan. Okay.
“一會兒，我在……”
"Later, I'm on a..."
托尼會來旁白，他會說，“這是什麼鬼東西?”
Tony would come to the narration, and he'd be like, "what is the shit?"
你懂我的意思嗎?所以…他會開始把東西劃掉。
You know what I mean? And so... He would start scratching things out.
你知道，一開始它是以這裡的一兩個詞或這裡的一兩個句子開始的。
And, you know, first it started with a word or two here or a sentence or two here.
你知道，然後他就變得，瘋狂起來。
You know, and then he became, like, maniacal about it.
“巡回售書，做電視節目，我以旅行為生。
"Book tours, the TV show, I travel for a living.
“我一直牢記《天空購物》雜志。
"I've committed to memory the skymall magazine.
電子澆水計時器，49.99美元。
"The electronic watering timer, $49.99.
“免稅限制:
"Duty-free restrictions:
一升酒精，兩盒煙
One liter alcohol, two cartons of smokes."
“補鞋匠甜點?我不這麼想。
"Cobbler for dessert? I don't think so.
"從機場到機場，從城市到城市"我開始覺得自己像現代版的威利·洛曼。
"Airport to airport, city to city, "I'm starting to feel like a modern-day Willy loman.
“從一個時區到另一個時區，從一個國家到另一個國家，這似乎就是我的生活。”
"Time zone to time zone, country to country, this, it appears, is my life."
他真的很理解，就像"這是我的延伸。
He really understood, like, "this is an extension of me.
“這是我寫作的延伸。
"This is an extension of my writing.
“我最好還是用我的聲音來寫。
"I better write in my voice.
“你知道，否則這聽起來會…我會聽起來像個旅行電視主持人而不是作家。”
"You know, otherwise this is gonna sound... I'm gonna sound like a tr-travel television host rather than a writer."
制作電視節目變得“創造性地令人滿意”。
"Making TV was becoming "creatively satisfying.
“我寫了這本書，但還是繼續拍攝。
"I wrote the book and yet continued filming.
“現在尾巴搖狗了。”
"The tail now wagged the dog."
“我迷上了旅行，迷上了看世界，”
"I was hooked on travel, on seeing the world,"
“而且是在我看到的條件下。”
"and on the terms I was seeing it."
"兩年的大部分時間我都在巡演"在此期間我的生活發生了改變。
"I was on the road for the better part of two years, "during which time everything in my life changed.
我不再做廚師了，這份工作的日常事務“一直是唯一”能讓我遠離混亂的東西。
"I stopped working as a chef, a job whose daily routines "have always been the only thing "that stood between me and chaos.
我的第一次婚姻開始破裂。”
My first marriage began to fall apart."
他們在一起快30年了。
They were together almost 30 years.
你知道，他是個傳統的浪漫主義者。
You know, he was a traditional romantic.
他相信你會遇到你的高中戀人，並與他們共度余生。
He believed that you could meet your high school sweetheart and spend the rest of your life with them.
他們就像，希德和南希。
They were like, you know, sid and Nancy.
他們就像兩個人密謀顛覆整個世界。
They were like two people conspiring against the world.
這是一種源於青春和叛逆的愛。
It was a love born out of youth and rebellion.
太好了。
Great.
南希，我希望你的離婚律師會密切關注這段錄像。
Nancy, I hope your divorce lawyer is paying close attention to this footage.
任何時候都可以傳喚這個團隊中的任何人。
Feel free to depose anyone on this crew at any time.
當然，這也是生命絢麗拼圖的一部分。
This, too, of course, is part of life's glorious mosaic.
南希對名利不感興趣，也不被名利束縛，但這對托尼來說就像是重生。
Nancy had no interest in fame or being tied to fame, but it just was like a rebirth for Tony.
就好像他死了又重生了。
It was like he died and-and was reborn.
我是說，這是一個有新生活的新人。
I mean, this was a new person with a new life.
我當時寫了一部犯罪小說裡面的人物對"白色尖樁籬笆牆般的生活"的渴望反映了我自己的生活"比我寫過的任何非小說作品都要真實得多。
"I wrote a crime novel "around that time in which the characters' yearnings "for a white-picket-fence kind of a life reflect my own "far more truthfully than any nonfiction I've ever written.
“在那之後不久，我殘忍地把我以前的生活全部燒掉了。”
"Shortly after that, I cruelly burned down my previous life in its entirety."
背景中漸漸消失的光芒，我想是機場的油庫…我們在我房間的陽台上，緊張地清空小酒吧，
That dying glow in the background is, uh, I think the fuel depot from the airport... There we are on the balcony in my room, nervously emptying out the minibar, uh,
看著飛機燃油在機場變質。
watching jet fuel cook off at the airport.
我們去那裡是為了給旅游頻道拍一個節目關於貝魯特是如何復興思想，情感和能量的，我們拍了兩個場景，然後事情很快就變糟了。
We had gone there to shoot a show for the travel channel about how Beirut was this renaissance of thought, feeling and energy, and we shot two scenes, and then shit went south really fast.
與以色列發生了邊境事件。
There was a border incident with Israel.
真主黨綁架了一些以色列士兵，基本上，我們卷入了一場戰爭。
Hezbollah had kidnapped some Israeli soldiers, and basically, uh, we got caught up in a war.
等一等。我,呃…托德，你到底有多惡心和焦慮?
Hold on. Let me, uh... Todd, exactly how disgusted and anxious are you?
我們能在這裡真是太幸運了。
We're damn lucky to be here.
我們把所有的時間都花在泳池邊，看著直升機進出。
We're spending all this time at the pool, watching helicopters come in and out.
對我們來說，這只是一場等待游戲。
It was just a waiting game for us.
我們不得不去地下室，因為我們身邊有很多炸彈。
We had to go in the basement because there was a lot of bombs by us.
他們拆掉了我們的房子。
They knocked down our house.
看看那些場景裡的我們。
You know, look at us in those scenes.
我們坐在泳池邊，曬黑皮膚，看一場戰爭。
You know, we're sitting around the pool, getting tan, you know, watching a war.
如果在整個經歷中有一個比喻，那就是……你知道，可能就是這樣。
If there's a single metaphor in this entire experience, that... You know, that's probably it.
不是奉承。
Not a flattering one.
當他們回來的時候，他說的第一件事就是，“我們不能拿這件事出洋相。”
When they arrived back, the first thing he said was, "we cannot make a show out of this.
我拒絕以這種方式利用這段經歷。”
I refuse to exploit this experience in that way."
不用說，網絡對此有不同的看法。
Needless to say, the network saw it differently.
這個故事沒有一個簡潔的總結。
There's just no neat sum-up to the story.
他停止做…這是我們剛才看到的玫瑰色總結。
He stopped doing the... Rosy sum-up of what we just saw.
他就停止了。
He just stopped.
在我開始周游世界的幾年裡，我發現自己變了。
In the few years since I've started to travel this world, I'd found myself changing.
我開始相信餐桌上的一切都是平等的。
I'd begun to believe that the dinner table was the great leveler.
現在我不那麼確定了。
Now I'm not so sure.
也許世界根本不是這樣的。
Maybe the world's not like that at all.
也許在現實世界裡，沒有攝像機，沒有快樂的食物，沒有旅游節目，所有人，無論好壞，都被同一個可怕的輪子壓扁了。
Maybe in the real world, the one without cameras and happy food and travel shows, everybody, the good and the bad together, are all crushed under the same terrible wheel.
我希望……我真希望我說錯了。
I hope... I really hope I'm wrong about that.
這種模稜兩可，正是他所接受的。
That ambiguity, that's what he embraced.
他媽的開放性就是答案所在。
Fucking open-endedness is where the answers are.
這是一次痛苦的經歷。
It was an embittering experience.
它讓我們所有人都在思考，生命中什麼才是重要的。
It got all of us thinking about, you know, what's important in life.
哦,是錄音。
Oh, it's recording.
哦,我的上帝。
Oh, my god.
你看起來像個白癡。
You look like an idiot.
拜托，說點什麼，安東尼·波登先生。
Come on, say something, Mr. Anthony bourdain.
這是我們的度假視頻，我們要給孩子們看。
This is, uh, our vacation video, and we're gonna show this to our children.
歡迎收看我的視頻。
Welcome to my video.
歡迎觀看我的第一部獨立電影。
Welcome to my first independent film.
我的春假。
My spring vacation.
喔,喔,喔!
Ow, ow, ow!
來吧，我在開車。
Come on, I'm driving.
那用英語怎麼說?
How do you say that in English?
這是一件壞事嗎?
Is this a bad thing?
托尼是單身，奧塔維婭為我工作。
Tony was single, and ottavia worked for me.
托尼打電話給我，他說"這女孩是誰，奧塔維婭"
Tony called me and he-he said, "who is this girl, ottavia?"
我說，“好吧，玩得開心。”
And I said, "well, have fun."
你知道，別當真。”
You know, don't take it seriously."
埃裡克認為，你知道，我們是那種偶爾的，約會的完美伴侶。
Eric thought, you know, we were the perfect match for those occasional, you know, rendezvous.
你開車像奶奶一樣。
You drive like grandma.
你什麼意思?奶奶是這樣開車的嗎?
What do you mean? Does grandma drive like this?
這裡，看，沒有手。
Oh, here, look, no hands.
哦,是的。
Oh, yeah.
我以為他會是個壞男孩，有點自大，雖然不是我想的那樣，但還是很討人喜歡。
I thought he was gonna be this bad boy, a little bit arrogant, and not what I was expecting but endearing nonetheless.
佩爾菲托。
Perfetto.
但你知道這個節目講的是什麼嗎?
But you know what the show's about?
——沒有。-這是關於我生命中的一個存在的十字路口。
- No. - It's about a, about a existential crossroads in my life.
你看起來已經很無聊了。
You look bored already.
我是。
I am.
你看到他們被迷住了。
You saw they were pretty smitten.
我是說，他一直都很欣賞女強人。
I mean, he always has really appreciated very strong women.
她不會放過他的。
She would cut him no slack.
這是一堆。
This is a load of.
這一幕最後會在剪輯室的地板上結束的幾率有多大?——零。
What are the chances this scene is gonna end up - on the cutting room floor? - Zero.
即使我們吵架。
Even if we fight.
那可是個不錯的電視節目，明白嗎?
Now, that would be good television, see?
我們應該戰斗。
We should fight.
幾個月後，我們在一家餐廳，她在餐桌上為他敬酒，我看到他眼裡含著淚水。
A couple of months later, we are in a restaurant, and she's toasting him at the table, and I see tears in his eyes.
真正的眼淚。
Real tears.
我們就想"天啊，他戀愛了"
And we're like, "oh, my god, he's in love."
好吧，我們來做點浪漫的事。
Okay, let's do some romantic thing.
什麼,就像……不。
What, like... no.
得到……托尼就像青少年一樣，第一次墜入愛河。
Get that... Tony was like the teenagers, like, falling in love for the first time.
他們換了衣服，換了聽的音樂，還有你以為你知道的他的某些部分也變了。
They changed their clothes and the music that they're listening to, and pieces of him that you thought you knew were... shifting.
托尼有孩子的時候你震驚了嗎?
Were you shocked when Tony had a kid?
我很震驚。
I was shocked.
我問他為什麼沒有孩子，他說……“我從沒見過自己這樣做，從來沒有。”
I had asked him how come he didn't have kids, and he's like... "It's just not something I ever see myself doing, ever."
在我人生的大部分時間裡，我都不會是個好父親。
For most of my life, I wouldn't have been a good father.
太自私，吸毒成癮。
Too self-involved, too messed-up on drugs.
也害怕。
And also afraid.
一想到要為一個孩子而害怕，你知道，我就受不了那種恐懼。
The thought of being frightened for a child, you know, I was not up to that kind of fear.
當我意識到他有多開心，多開心，多興奮他就要當爸爸了，我所有的懷疑都煙消雲散了。
Any doubts I might have had kind of dissipated when I realized how happy, how happy, excited he was that he was gonna become a father.
——沒有電話。——沒有電話嗎?
- No phone. - No phone?
好吧。好吧。沒關系。
Okay. Okay. That's okay.
——這是好嗎?——沒關系。
- That's okay? - That's okay.
——是嗎?沒關系,爸爸?- - - - - -來吧。來吧。
- Yeah? It's okay, dada? - Come on. Come on.
-好吧，擁抱一下?- - - - - -來吧。
- Okay, a little hug? - Come on.
來吧,現在。好吧,好吧。
Come on, now. Okay, okay.
——好吧,好吧。——好的。
- Okay, okay. - Okay.
來吧。來吧,光電。
Come on. Come on, appa.
——光電。——光電?那你的阿柏呢?
- Appa. - Appa? What about your appa?
一個,兩個,三個。
One, two, three.
你知道我們說的是□
□ You know we're talking □
-拜托，拜托。-□關於醫生。□
- Come on, come on. - □ 'bout the doctor. □
但是醫生是什麼樣的呢?
But what does the doctor look like?
嗯,你好。我是托尼博士。
Well, hello. I'm Dr. Tony.
這裡有什麼問題嗎?
What seems to be the problem here?
我是來幫你康復的。
I'm here to help you get all better.
——萬歲!——是的!
- Hooray! - Yeah!
我們應該幫助所有需要幫助的人。
We should help all people when they need help.
這倒提醒我了，我得回去了。
Hey, that reminds me, I have to get back.
再見。
Bye.
這就是我的生活。
This is my life.
我醒來。
I wake up.
我陪女兒去夏令營。
I walk my daughter to her summer camp.
我本來有幾分鍾的正常家庭生活，然後我就乘電梯下樓，然後又……喲,安東尼!老板，你好嗎?
You know, I have a few minutes of normal family life, then I, like, take the elevator downstairs, and there's yet another... Yo, Anthony! How you doing, boss?
嘿，怎麼了，伙計?
Hey, what's up, man?
你在工作嗎?
Are you on the job?
這家伙的節目在電視上是最棒的。
Yo, this guy's got the best show on TV.
托尼真的很出名。
Tony got really famous.
好像每兩分鍾就有一個人朝他走過去。
Like, every two minutes, it seemed, someone's going up to him.
“嘿。”
"Hey."
"托尼，我是你的超級粉絲"
You know, "Tony, I'm a huge fan."
“我能拍張照片嗎?”
"Can I take a photo?
“你能和我談談嗎?”
"Can you talk to me?
有什麼旅游小貼士嗎?我會……”
What are, what-what are some travel tips? Would I..."
只是不停的，不停的彈幕。
It-it was just incessant, nonstop barrage.
他有了孩子，想做奧塔維亞的好丈夫，但一切都變了。
He got a kid and he wanted to be a good husband to ottavia, and... everything changed, man.
對他來說。
For him.
我是食物壞小子托尼·波登。
I'm food bad boy Tony bourdain.
我沒有不去的地方，也沒有不吃的東西，只要我的薪水是綠寶石我的酒店房間裡有個能射熱香檳的坐浴盆。
There's nowhere I won't go and nothing I won't eat, as long as I'm paid in emeralds and my hotel room has a bidet that shoots warm champagne.
女士們先生們，有請安東尼·波登。
Ladies and gentlemen, Anthony bourdain.
然後我就想"托尼，搞什麼鬼，伙計?
And that's when I was like, "Tony, like, what the fuck, man?
“比如，你是如何保持冷靜和鎮定的，而且你人很好?”
"Like, how do you maintain your cool and your composure and you're nice?"
我永遠不會忘記這件事。他說,“聽。
I'll never forget this. He's like, "listen.
"我對人友善，對人親切，"如果這是我的工作，那肯定比在一家境況不佳的餐廳當二等廚師強"
"Me being nice to someone and being gracious to them, "if that's my job, it certainly beats being middling line cook at a struggling restaurant."
你有過正常的生活嗎?
Do you have anything resembling a normal life?
不。
No.
我這麼問是因為我的答案是否定的。
I'm asking this 'cause the answer for me is no.
我想說沒有，因為我剛拜訪了我的朋友。
I want to say no, 'cause I just visited my friends.
我很多年沒見過他們了。
I haven't seen them in many years.
——正確的。-我覺得我無法聯系。
- Right. - And I felt I just... I couldn't relate.
-我是說，就像…-我知道，我知道
- I mean, it's like... - I know, I know.
我能理解，但是…是的。
And I-I understand those, but-but, but... yeah.
我是一個怪胎。
I'm a freak.
-他們只…——該死的地獄。耶穌。
- They only... - Fucking hell. Jesus.
哦，這很有趣嗎?
Oh, is this so interesting?
我們還在等什麼?
What are we waiting for?
有……我們時刻准備著。
Is there... We're always at the ready.
我隨時都可能生下一個巨大的外星寶寶。
I'm about to give birth to a big fucking alien baby at any moment.
會很轟動的。
It's-it's gonna be huge.
好吧，那我們休息五分鍾吧。
All right, why don't we take five, then.
- 5。——天哪。耶穌。
- Take five. - Holy crap. Jesus.
和你……你有多少天的直擊時間?
And you're... How many days of straight shooting you have?
別問我這個。
Don't ask me that.
國際毒梟湯姆·維塔萊最近在阿姆斯特丹被捕。
The international narco trafficker Tom vitale was arrested in Amsterdam just recently.
在當地警局的檢查中，他們發現他吞下了破紀錄的90博塔可卡因。
On examination at the local precinct, they found he'd swallowed a record-breaking 90 bolitas of cocaine.
在我看來，讓它進入節目的是最不有趣的……旅行的一部分。
What made it into the shows was, as far as I was concerned, the least interesting... Parts of the trip.
歡迎來到又一集24小時做愛。
Welcome to another episode of 24-hour fuck-over.
他在很多方面都是個控制狂。
He was a control freak in a lot of ways.
和他爭論你是贏不了的。
You couldn't win an argument with him.
僅僅因為有一個想法，他就會挑戰它。
Just because there was an idea, he would challenge it.
你有台詞給我嗎?
Do you have any lines for me?
也許你能給我點吃的。
Maybe you can feed me something.
羅馬在黃昏。沒有比這更好的地方了，不是嗎?
Rome at dusk. There's really no place like it, is there?
空氣中彌漫著浪漫氣息。
Uh, romance is in the air.
-誰說的?-我們只在這裡待兩天
- Who says that? - We're here for two days.
什麼時候?我這輩子什麼時候說過這話?
When? When at any point in my life have I ever said that?
偶爾你會受到啟發，說些好聽的話讓我潸然淚下。
Occasionally you feel inspired and you say something really nice that makes me tear up.
我想今天不會了。
Not today, I guess.
要我說，他的廢話晴雨表一般都非常敏感。
Well, I would say his barometer for bullshit in general was extremely sensitive.
但如果他覺得我們在扯淡，我是說，那就像是最大的罪，對吧?
But if he felt we were bullshitting, I mean, that's like kind of the ultimate sin, right?
你要沿著運河走…你得跟在他後面指揮。
You're gonna walk down along the canal... You'd have to sort of lead from behind with him.
這是什麼樣的法西斯政權?
What kind of fascist regime is this?
因為當托尼想離開時，他就會離開。
Because when Tony wanted to leave, Tony would leave.
我是說，阻止他得靠身體。
I mean, stopping him had to be physical.
比如把我的身體擋在他和逃跑路線之間。
Like putting my body in between him and the escape route.
讓他離我遠點。
Keep him away from me.
不,不,不。
No, no, no.
是的，我受夠了，伙計。
Yeah, I've had enough, man.
太,太滿不在乎。
Too, too fucked-up.
我的一天都毀了。
Well, my day's ruined.
——真的嗎?——沒有。
- Really? - No.
——好的。再見。-我要哭了。
- All right. Goodbye. - I'm gonna burst into tears.
是啊，很不錯吧?
Yeah, that's pretty good, huh?
一開始，它只是。
In the beginning, it was just.
克裡斯和莉迪亞和他一起射擊。
Chris and Lydia shooting with him.
他們這樣做了好幾年，然後引進了一整個團隊的人，其中很多人一直堅持到最後。
They did that for several years and then brought in a whole team of people, many of them who stuck around to the end.
這是給你的。
This is for you.
哦!
Oh!
-你以後可能需要這個。-我會的
- You might need this later. - Oh, I will.
那幾乎是我人生中最形成期的歲月。
It was pretty much the most formative years of my life.
會有流血的。
There will be blood.
在節目中有一些互相爭斗的團隊。
There were these battling sort of teams on the show.
——嗨,黛安娜。——黛安娜。
- Hi, Diane. - Diane.
嘿!嘿!
Hey! Hey!
扎克推出了一個叫換鏡頭的小玩意。
Zach introduced a little something called the-the lens change.
我想托尼喜歡我有幾個原因。
I think Tony liked me for a couple reasons.
一是，你知道，我喜歡和托尼亂搞。
One was that, you know, I enjoyed fucking with Tony.
你知道嗎?我是說，那是…我們都用自己的方式惹過他。
You know? I mean, it was... Uh, we all sort of fucked with him in our own ways.
你知道，競爭非常激烈，所以每一集都有壓力。
You know, it was very competitive, and so the bar got pushed every single episode.
托尼什麼都參與了。
Tony was in on everything.
每一場演出都很重要。
Every show was something that was important.
每一場演出都有他的用心。
Every show had his care in it.
每一場演出都可能有他的憤怒。
Every show potentially had his wrath.
我收到過多少封郵件，"讓編輯去死吧"
I mean, how many emails I got, "tell editor to UN-fuck itself."
我得把這句話翻譯給編輯。
And I had to translate that to the editor.
他會說，最大的罪惡是平庸。
He would say that the greatest sin is mediocrity.
“有抱負的平庸。
"Aspiring to mediocrity.
“一部好電視劇的結局有一個殘酷的，不可避免的，而且完全可以預測的軌跡”。
"There is a grim, inevitable "and all too predictable trajectory "to the passage of a good episode of television.
“人們並不像你的奴才們認為的那麼愚蠢。
"People aren't as stupid as your minions clearly believe.
"他們不需要真相" "用無意義的陳詞濫調"或平淡無奇的總結"
"They don't need the truth "pounded home with meaningless platitudes "or bland, generic sum-ups.
他們會得到它。”
They'll get it."
它持續了好幾頁。
And it goes on for several pages.
“不要讓這些松鼠球呆子為所欲為”。
"Don't empower these squirrel-balled nerds "by letting them get their way.
"他們會像饑餓的鴨子一樣"把這個節目啃個精光。
"They will then nibble this show to death "like hungry ducks.
一如既往，致以最良好的祝願和敬意，托尼。”
As always, best wishes and respect, Tony."
這封信是寫給他真正喜歡和尊敬的人的。
And this was written to somebody he truly liked and respected.
如果每個人都喜歡這個節目，他會很煩惱。
It bothered him if everyone liked the show.
他說"這應該能引起討論"
He was like, "it should create conversation."
他多大了?
How old is he?
他還記得飛機嗎?
D-Does he even remember the planes?
他還是個孩子。
He was a child.
他不記得。
He doesn't remember.
不記得。這些年來……他是一個令人震驚的反文化聲音。
Doesn't remember. All these years... He was a shockingly countercultural voice.
我是說，我和他合作過的很多國家都還在應對美國所做的一切所帶來的後果。
I mean, so many of the countries I worked in with him were still dealing with the fallout from whatever america had done.
對他來說，失去了一切，因為他是…一家之主，養活全家。
For him, it's losing everything, uh, because he's the... The head of the family, feeding the family.
所以在失去雙臂和雙腿之後，這對他來說是一場巨大的災難。
Um, so after losing his arms and his legs, uh, it's-it's a great disaster for his life.
他想知道你是否害怕看到現實。
Uh, he wants to know if you are afraid of seeing the-the reality.
啊。害怕嗎?
Ah. Afraid?
嗯,哦,不。
Um, uh, no.
很疼，但我覺得這很合適。
It-it hurts, but I think that's appropriate.
你知道，它應該。我認為美國人…每個美國人都應該看到戰爭的結果。
You know, it should. I think Americans... Every American should see the results of war.
我想是…至少我能做的是睜開眼睛看看這個世界。
I think it's, uh... the least I can do is to-to see the world with open eyes.
你會注意到，總的來說，我不是我自己。
You'll notice that, in general, I'm not myself.
你那刻薄的態度呢?
Where's the snark, the attitude?
你覺得這個怎麼樣?
Well, what do you say to this?
我真的不知道。
I honestly don't know.
人不是統計數據。
People are not statistics.
當然，展示這些小東西是有價值的。
Surely there's value in-in showing the little things.
她的生意怎麼樣?你能問問她嗎?
How's business for her? Uh, can you ask her?
這次不太好。
Not re... Not really good this time.
——不是好嗎?——沒有。
- Not good? - No.
我的意思是，這個國家的情況是，人們沒有任何收入，沒有錢，所以他們不能在街上買食物。
I mean, the country's situation, people don't have any income, any money, so they can't buy food in the street.
你可以想象一下。
So you can imagine that.
,看看…所以你才會看到很多人在這裡乞討。
That, see... That why you see a lot of guys here begging, you know.
“你能給我買些食物嗎?”你能給我點什麼嗎?”
"Can you buy me some food? Can you give me something?"
我們處理的最大的問題是，你知道的，像牆上的蒼蠅一樣進入一個地方，卻沒有任何效果。
The biggest issue that we dealt with was trying to be, you know, the fly on the wall and-and going into a place and not having an effect.
比如，這一集就是一個很好的例子，它只是想要幫助別人，而且它還昂起了它丑陋的頭。
Like, this episode is a prime example of just trying to help, and it rearing its ugly head.
我們有這麼多剩菜。
We have all this leftover food.
托尼說，我們就把它給這裡的人吧
Tony's like, "let's just give it to the people here."
你知道，他們餓了，當然混亂隨之而來。
You know, they're hungry, and of course mayhem ensued.
大一點的孩子，就像是，把小一點的孩子趕出隊列，這是一個非常丑陋的場景。
Larger kids were just, like, throwing younger kids out of the line, and it was a very ugly scenario.
我想托尼最終明白了不僅僅是食物。
I think Tony ultimately saw that it wasn't just food.
這個世界上有痛苦，而且似乎無處不在。
There's suffering in this world, and that seems to be omnipresent.
你怎麼花時間和別人相處，你怎麼同情他們的困境…這怎麼能不從根本上改變你呢?
How do you spend time with people and-and-and you empathize with their plight... How does that not change you fundamentally?
喲。喲。
Whee. Whee.
你要去外太空?
You going to outer space?
是的。
Yes.
會更高。
Going higher.
他一年要出差250天，你知道，當你回家的時候，你必須做一個丈夫，你必須做一個父親。
He was traveling 250 days a year, and, you know, when you come back home, you have to be a husband, you have to be a father.
在僅有的一點時間裡，他非常專心。
With the little time he had, he was very attentive.
海灘上的沙堡，一整天。
Sandcastles on the beach, all day long.
我想這對他來說是一個驚喜和沖擊，在他晚年，能體驗到這樣的愛。
I think it was a surprise and shock for him, that late in life, to experience that kind of love.
我能用這只手嗎?
Can I use this hand?
沒關系。用這只手。
That's okay. Use that hand.
我們把它拉出來，用手抓面包屑。
We'll pull that out and use that hand for the crumbs.
沒關系。
It's okay.
這深深打動了他。
It moved him to his core.
我覺得他一直都意識到，不想把事情搞砸。
And I think he was constantly aware of, like, not wanting to screw it up.
你現在真的在這個國家嗎，還是這只是海市蜃樓?
Are you really in this country right now, or is this a mirage?
我是我的特技替身。
I-I am my stunt double.
你就不能找個好看點的嗎?
Couldn't you get someone better-looking?
是的。哦!
Yeah. Oh!
該劇的粉絲們認為他擁有世界上最偉大的工作，但這是一份永遠無法逃避的工作。
Fans of the show think he had the greatest job in the world, but it was one that there was no way to ever escape from.
一天回家都不能不是安東尼·波登。
Couldn't really go home for a day and not be Anthony bourdain.
你要做什麼樣的?
What kind are you making?
餅干。哪一種最好?
Cookie. What's the best kind?
我不知道。你遵守童工法了嗎?
I don't know. Uh, are you observing child labor laws?
他的女兒以前經常開玩笑說，“我是安東尼·波登。”
His daughter used to do this joke where she would get up and say, "I'm Anthony bourdain."
嗨。我叫安東尼·波登。
Hi. My name's Anthony bourdain.
“你可能在諸如……之類的電視節目中認識我。”
"You may know me from such TV shows as..."
也許你是在一些節目裡認識我的，呃…她知道她父親和安東尼·波登是兩個截然不同的人。
Maybe you know me from such shows as, uh... She knew that her father and Anthony bourdain were very separate entities.
你挖鼻子挖得可真費勁，小姑娘。
You're picking that nose pretty hard there, young lady.
哦!上帝!
Oh! God!
“我不想再扮酷了。
"I'm through being cool.
或者，更准確地說，我已經不再“考慮任何人都可以考慮從我身邊散發或居住的酷的可能性”。
"Or, more accurately, I'm through "entertaining the notion that anybody could even "consider the possibility of coolness emanating from or residing anywhere near me."
所有人都對著鏡頭。
Everybody kick to the camera.
Hi-yah !
Hi-yah!
"酷的真諦"就是不關心。
"The essence of cool, after all, "is not giving a fuck.
讓我們面對現實吧，我現在絕對在乎了。”
And let's face it, I most definitely give a fuck now."
你知道，我這輩子，就像個孩子鼻子緊貼著玻璃，就像，在想，有個孩子，一個正常的家庭是什麼感覺
You know, my whole life, I was like a kid with my nose pressed against the glass, like, wondering, you know, "what must it be like to, like, "have a kid and, you know, a normal family
“然後，穿著這條傻乎乎的圍裙站在後院烤漢堡?”
"and-and stand in the backyard with this silly apron, you know, barbecuing burgers?"
-所以當我發現…-我能照張相嗎?
- And so when I find... - Can I get a picture of that?
當我發現自己這麼做的時候，我就會開心得可笑又愚蠢。
When I find myself doing that, I am, like, ridiculously, stupid happy.
我現在做了很多很酷的事。
Like, I do a lot of pretty cool shit now.
我周游世界，我看到了所有神奇的事物，但我最開心的是當我站在後院，就像電視裡的爸爸，因為……我感覺正常。
I travel all over the world, I see all these amazing things, but I'm never happier than when I'm standing in-in the backyard being, like, TV dad, because... I-I feel normal.
你知道嗎?不管那是什麼意思。
You know? Whatever the hell that means.
那是什麼意思?
Yeah, what does that mean?
我過著奇怪的生活。
I live a very strange life.
當我回家的時候，我會努力地做飯來彌補。
I try to make up for it when I go home by cooking aggressively.
比如，我試圖用食物殺死我周圍的人。
Like, I try to kill people around me with food.
就像"吃，吃，你懂的。
You know, like, "eat, eat, you know.
你為什麼不吃飯?你不愛我嗎?”
Why aren't you eating? Don't you love me?"
他在國內的生活中游手好閒，但那種對國外生活經歷的渴望……你知道，就好像如果他不在那裡，一切就會溜走……同樣偉大。
He straddled the world of being the domestic guy, but that pull for the experience outside... You know, like as if it was gonna slip away if he wasn't there... Was equally as great.
他總是匆匆忙忙的。
He was always rushing.
他到處跑。
He was rushing everywhere.
他急著進入現場。
He was rushing to get into the scene.
他急著要離開現場。
He was rushing to get out of the scene.
急著離開這個國家。
Rushing to get out of the country.
急著去下一個地方，即使他無處可去。
Rushing to go somewhere next, even if he had nowhere to go.
□抽時間……□
□ Making time... □
獨自一人在地球上旅行是我習慣的旅行方式。
Traveling the earth alone is what I'm accustomed to being on a tour.
作為父親，我們因為那種感覺而團結在一起，那種感覺就像，“我在這裡是為了讓自己露出一部分。”
And as fathers, we bonded over that feeling and feeling like, "I'm here to give a piece of myself away."
隨著時間的推移，這可能會變得很困難。
And, um, as the years go on, that can be difficult.
□每個人離開……□
□ Everybody leaving... □
——關閉。——風。那是風。
- Close. - The wind. That was the wind.
正確的。我們得，我們得，把這個因素考慮進去。
Right. We got to, we got to, you know, factor that in.
好了。
There we go.
我們一見如故。
And we just hit it off.
你怎麼稱呼永恆的樂觀主義者?
What do you call an eternal optimist?
有呼機的手風琴演奏者。
An accordion player with a beeper.
交朋友很難。
It's hard to make friends.
站在槍尖上，就像在尋求孤獨。
To be at the tip of the spear, it's like asking for loneliness.
哦!
Oh!
哦,是的。
Oh, yeah.
那混蛋已經失血過多了。
That motherfucker bled out already.
直刺頸靜脈。
Straight to the jugular.
□閉上你的眼睛□
□ Closing your eyes □
□找更多的借口□
□ making more excuses □
□扯羊毛…□
□ pulling the wool... □
-是的。-能再來三個嗎?
- Yeah. - Can you make it three?
-好吧，干杯。——干杯。
- Well, cheers to that. - Cheers.
我總是在想"喲，呵，呵，我要過海盜的生活"
I always think of, "yo, ho, ho, a pirate's life for me."
我就是這麼想的。
That's-that's what I think.
我的意思是,那是……但你一直在巡演…?
I mean, that's... But you've been, you've been touring for...?
從我18歲開始，是的。
Since I was 18, yeah.
你知道嗎?
You know?
你知道，但這很奇怪。
You know, but it's weird.
我要回家……我開心了一個星期，然後我就開始變得，像瘋了一樣，好像我應該做點什麼。
I-I'm home for... i'm ridiculously happy for a week, and then I start getting, like, crazy, like I should be doing something.
我稱之為苦樂參半的詛咒。
I call it the bittersweet curse.
沒有什麼比回家更好的感覺了。
Nothing feels better than going home.
沒有什麼比離開家更好的感覺了。
And nothing feels better than leaving home.
-你說對了——你知道嗎?
- Yeah, you got a point. - You know?
我喜歡看著他在生活中逐漸獲得影響力。
I loved watching him pick up influence as he went along through life.
他是一個偉大的美國故事講述者，他一開始是一個偷窺狂。
He's a great American storyteller, and he started off as a voyeur.
他正在看這些，並詳細描述你們所看到的偉大故事。
He's watching these and detailing these great tales of what you're seeing.
然後，突然間，他開始活在他所講述的故事中。
And then, all of a sudden, he's starting to live those stories that he's telling.
他開始往裡面看了。
He's starting to look inside.
"我想我之前說過"
"I think I said earlier"
"我要告訴你真相。"
"that I was gonna tell you the truth."
“這是其中的一部分。”
"This is part of it."
“我不能勝任這份工作。
"I was unqualified for the job.
“我當時處在水深火熱之中。
"I was in deep waters and fast-flowing ones at that.
洋流隨時可能在沒有預警的情況下發生變化。”
The currents could change at any time without warning."
"和很多旅行者一樣，我開始從窗外向內看，"開始透過越來越窄的鏡片看外面發生了什麼"
"Like a lot of travelers, I started to turn inward "from the view out the window, "started to see what was going on out there through an ever-narrowing lens."
據說我應該忠於我選擇的噩夢。
It is written that I should be loyal to the nightmare of my choice.
我想我現在明白那是什麼意思了。
I think I now understand what that means.
你想當我的飛行員?
You want to be my pilot?
是的。
Yeah.
我看不出有什麼問題。
I don't see what the problem is.
我覺得天氣不錯。
Weather looks fine to me.
我相信我們會沒事的。
I'm sure we'll be fine.
哇。好了。
Wow. Nice.
安全形勢好，天氣不太好。
Security situation good, weather not so good.
順便問一下，你害怕嗎?
Are you frightened, by the way?
是啊，看看他。看著他。他非常害怕。
Yeah, look at him. Look at him. He's scared shitless.
我不喜歡坐飛機。
I don't like flying.
我認為剛果，毫無疑問，是我們節目中最危險的地方。
I think that the Congo was, without question, the most dangerous place we ever made the show.
這是一件無法做到的事。
It was something that couldn't be done.
這是很重要的一部分，我們總會想辦法去做一些我們做不到的事情。
That was a big part of it, and we're always gonna figure out a way to do something that couldn't be done.
每個人都能得到他想要的一切。
Everyone gets everything he wants.
我想看看剛果。
I wanted to see the Congo.
因為我的罪過，他們讓我。
And for my sins, they let me.
這是我小時候讀到過的地方。
This is a place I read about as a boy.
在《黑暗之心》中，康拉德把它描述為一條扭曲的蛇，它的頭在大西洋，尾巴深埋在非洲的心髒。
In heart of darkness, Conrad described it as a twisting snake with its head in the Atlantic ocean and its tail buried deep in Africa's heart.
剛果實現了一個巨大的夢想。
Congo was a fulfillment of an enormous dream.
在我們小小的幻想中，我們正在經歷末日時刻。
In our little fantasy, we were having our apocalypse now moment.
我們租了條可靠的船，我將任命你為威拉德船長。
We've rented a trusty vessel, and I shall dub thee the captain Willard.
托尼在尋找方法讓自己不僅能理解世界還能理解自己。
Tony was finding ways to push himself towards his not just understanding of the world but understanding of himself.
你是刺客嗎?
Are you an assassin?
我是一個士兵。
I'm a soldier.
就像，他在那部電影裡是哪個角色?
It's like, which character is he in that film?
他們說我的方法不合理。
They say my methods are unsound.
我的方法不合理嗎?
Are my methods unsound?
你認為我的方法不合理嗎?
Do you think my methods are unsound?
上校，我沒看到任何方法。
I haven't seen any method at all, colonel.
在剛果，他是一個把自己推入一個沒有法律、沒有秩序、沒有結構的瘋狂世界的人。
In Congo, he got to be someone who has pushed himself into the lunacy of a world without law, without order, without structure.
他拿著一把三英尺的大砍刀站在那裡指揮刺殺雞群。
He got to stand there with a three-foot machete and direct the assassination of chickens.
當你真正深入旅行的時候，我認為你會有一種渴望，想要去撓它，它就在那個信封的邊緣，在那個混亂統治的地方。
When you get really deep into travel, I think there's an itch that you want to scratch that is out on the edge of that envelope, where chaos rules.
因為它剝去了我們生活中所有的功能技巧，只留下感官體驗。
Because it strips away all of the functional artifice of how we go through our life, and it leaves you with just the sensory experience.
著名廚師和暢銷書作家安東尼·波登(Anthony bourdain)有一個新計劃，部分未知，它展示了波登發現一個國家或文化精髓的天賦。
Anthony bourdain, the renowned chef and best-selling author, has a new program, parts unknown, and it showcases bourdain's gift for finding the essence of a country or a culture.
是關於新聞業，還是關於旅游業?
Is it about the journalism, or is it about the tourism?
是關於人嗎?是關於食物嗎?
Is it about the people? Is it about the food?
這是食物、政治和堅定的個人觀點的奇怪結合。
It's a strange combination of food, politics and a decisively personal point of view.
他在以色列、巴勒斯坦領土、墨西哥和法國裡昂的報告簡直棒極了。
His reports from Israel, the Palestinian Territories, Mexico and Lyon, France, were simply superb.
他旅行了大約66.2萬英裡。環游世界26次。
He's traveled roughly 662,000 miles... Around the globe 26 times.
其實我去丹吉爾是因為你去過那裡。
Uh, you know, I actually went to tangier because you had gone there.
你對我的影響很大。
And you've had a big impact on me.
托尼很清楚自己有提升別人聲音的能力。
Tony was very aware of his own ability to promote other people's voices.
但我確實認為，即使我們搬到CNN，他贏得了一個皮博迪獎和幾個艾美獎，他開始質疑誰從這些節目中受益。
But I do think that, even though we moved to CNN, he won a peabody and several emmys, he began to question who was benefiting from these shows.
好吧，那我們就用電視拍張照片。
Okay, so we're just gonna set up a shot with the TV.
我躺在床上看CNN。
Me laying on the bed, watching CNN.
——好的。——利比亞的消息。
- Okay. - Libya news.
這是CNN。
This is CNN.
今天是1月25日，星期五。
It is Friday, January the 25th.
我是克裡斯蒂·盧·斯托特。這是……我不是新聞迷。
I'm kristie lu stout. This is... I'm not a news fan.
我不是記者。
I'm not a journalist.
我不是一個擁護者。我不是教育家。
I'm not an advocate. I'm not an educator.
我不是想激勵你或者…我沒有政治目的。
I'm not looking to inspire or, uh... I don't have a political agenda.
如果說有什麼不同的話，那就是我非常喜歡去一個地方思考一件事，結果卻完全錯了。
If anything, I like very much going to a place thinking one thing and being completely wrong about all of it.
他是一名記者，政治人士，但他是一個講故事的人。
He was a journalist and he was political, but he was a storyteller.
我想，他當時並沒有意識到自己有多麼政治化。
And he didn't realize, I think, how political he was.
我們尤其傾向於看到中東和非洲的地方。我們只有在糟糕的事情發生時才會看到它們。
We tend to see places in the middle east and Africa in particular... We only see them when bad things happen.
如果你關注新聞，你會想起阿爾及利亞的綁架，突尼斯的動亂，南部的恐怖分子，埃及的致命暴亂，
If you just follow the news, you'll be reminded about kidnappings in Algeria, unrest in Tunisia, terrorist cells to the south, deadly riots in Egypt,
當然還有伊斯蘭極端分子在班加西發動的襲擊，導致美國大使喪生。
and of course islamic extremist attacks in Benghazi that killed the U.S. ambassador.
所有這些都是非常現實的問題。
All those things are very real concerns.
但如果你只看新聞，你可能會錯過更大的圖景。
But if you only look at what's on the news, you can miss maybe what's a bigger picture.
你可以看到他越來越多地旅行。
You can literally see it as he goes and travels more and more and more.
根本就不是為了吃，你知道嗎?
It was almost never about food, you know?
我覺得是托尼在學習如何成為一個更好的人。
I think it was about Tony learning how to be a better person.
你知道，我每天都在小方面模仿基督。
You know, I try to emulate Christ in small ways every day.
你會怎麼做?
You do?
是的。
Yeah.
你不能告訴嗎?
Can't you tell?
我的意思是，以一種完全不失禮的方式。
And I mean that in a, in a completely non-disrespectful way.
不，不，我能想象。
No, no, I can imagine.
我是說，你在努力。
I mean, you're trying.
你的節目鼓舞了很多人。
You are inspiring so many people with the show.
你有一個好的因果報應。
You have a good Karma.
真不敢相信你會這麼說。
Can't believe you say that.
-是的。——好業力呢?
- Yeah. - Good Karma?
我想是的。
I think so.
嗯…-你不擔心嗎?-這是一個好的因果報應。
Well... - Doesn't this concern you... - This is a good Karma.
作為佛教?
As a Buddhist?
-看，我們現在在普羅旺斯。-是的。
- Look we're sitting here in provence. - Yeah.
——所以呢?-等一下。
- So? - Wait a minute.
-我們剛吃了一頓很棒的飯。-是的。
- We just had this fantastic meal. - Yeah.
2010年之後的2011年。
We're moving on to the 2011 after the 2010.
誠然，對你來說，生活是相當甜蜜的。
Life, admittedly for you, has been pretty sweet.
是的。
Yeah.
-你不擔心嗎?——沒有。
- Isn't that worrying to you? - No.
我們坐在普羅旺斯。就像酒標一樣。
We're sitting in provence. It's like a wine label.
來世不可能比這更好。
The next life cannot possibly be better than this.
可能會很糟糕。
It's probably gonna suck.
好好享受這一刻吧，埃裡克。
Enjoy every minute of this now, Eric.
和祈禱。
And pray.
祈禱吧，祈禱就這樣吧，因為如果你是對的還有來生，我們就完了，朋友。
Pray, pray that this is it, because if you're right and there is a next life, we are fucked, my friend.
我可能會變成海參，但你會變成約克犬。
I may come back as a sea cucumber, but you're coming back as, like, a yorkie.
或者，你知道，如果你幸運的話。
Or, you know, if you're lucky.
我要約克犬。
I'll take the yorkie.
到最後，托尼就會變得很黑暗，伙計。
At the end of the day, Tony's dark as fuck, man.
舉個例子。
Give you an example.
每個人都問托尼最喜歡什麼音樂，他總是給出同樣的狗屁答案，比如《96個謎》或者那首該死的歌。
Like, everyone asked Tony's fucking favorite music, and he would always give the same bullshit answers, like, uh, uh, "96 mysterios" or that fucking song.
-他喜歡那首歌。——“96年眼淚。”
- He loved that song. - "96 tears."
“96的眼淚。”
"96 tears."
他喜歡"超級蒼蠅"
And he loved, um, "super fly"
還有柯蒂斯·梅菲爾德的原聲帶
and, um, and Curtis Mayfield's soundtrack.
這群人裡沒有鎮定劑。
There's no downers in the fucking bunch.
這是托尼告訴我的他最喜歡的歌。
This was what Tony told me was his favorite song.
他愛死這首歌了。
He loved this fucking song.
這是一首很棒的歌。
It's a great song.
但這是海洛因音樂。
But it's heroin music.
70年代初，這是我住的地方。
In the early '70s, this is where I lived.
那時候，如果你給我們帶海洛因，我們會說"太酷了"
You know, back then, if you brought us heroin, we would've said, "ah, cool.
我將完全…我也想嘗嘗。”
I'll totally... I would like to try some of that."
我並不是無意中沉迷其中，或者是不小心上癮了，你知道的，“哦，真的上癮了?”
It wasn't like I fell into it or accidentally got addicted or, you know, "oh, really, it's addicting?
哎呀，這是怎麼回事?”不,我知道。
Gee, how'd that happen?" No, I knew.
他從未真正處理過不安全感以及所有讓他走上那條路的問題。
He never really dealt with the insecurity and all the issues that put him down that road to begin with.
你知道，跟喬說這件事就容易多了，因為，那個混蛋太黑暗了。
You know, it's a lot easier when you talk to choe about this, 'cause, like, that motherfucker is so dark.
□從我的頭頂飛過……□
□ Flying over my head... □
大家都忘了安東尼·波登是個癮君子。
People forget Anthony bourdain was a junkie.
他是個癮君子，我也是。
Like, he's a drug addict, and I'm also a junkie.
我不吸毒，但我什麼都做。
I don't do drugs, but I do everything else.
暴食者匿名，債務人匿名，賭徒匿名，性成癮者匿名，性和愛情成癮者匿名。
Overeaters anonymous, debtors anonymous, gamblers anonymous, sex addicts anonymous, sex and love addicts anonymous.
我參加了所有的互助會。
Uh, I-I go to all the meetings.
我要告訴你一件我很丟臉的事。
I'll tell you something really shameful about myself.
我第一次注射的時候，對著鏡子裡的自己咧著嘴笑。
The first time I shot up, I looked at myself in the mirror with a big grin.
你知道，我身上缺了點什麼。
You know, something was missing in me.
我內心有些想成為一個癮君子。
Some part of me wanted to be a dope fiend.
我的一生都是為了那一刻。
My whole life was leading up to that point.
在我看來，這是我成為藝術家的第一步。
In my mind, it was my first step towards being an artist.
你認為某種程度的不滿意或不快樂是創造過程中不可分割的一部分嗎?
Do you think a-a certain level of dissatisfaction or unhappiness is an integral part of the creative process?
我認為即使是偉大的藝術也可以在你快樂的時候創造出來，但我認為宇宙中最好的藝術是通過強烈的痛苦創造出來的。
I think even great art can be created when you're happy, but I think the best art in the universe is created through intense suffering.
那麼，你會讓自己一直處於痛苦之中嗎?
So then, do you put yourself in a situation where you're constantly in pain?
這個問題的答案是肯定的。
And the answer to that question is yes.
這就是我認識的所有人。
That's just about everybody I know.
我不知道這說明了我什麼。
I don't know what this says about me.
我想那是我和他的第一次對話。
I think it was one of the first conversations I ever had with him.
我就想，嘿，我知道我才剛認識你，但除了你，我不知道還有誰戒毒了。
"I was like," hey, I know I'm just meeting you, "but I-I don't know one heroin addict "that has quit cold Turkey besides you.
告訴我你是怎麼做到的。”
Tell me how you did it."
我挺過去了，但是，你知道，我的案子，就像我看著鏡子，然後我…我看到了值得拯救的人，或者是我想要努力去拯救的人。
I got through, but, you know, my case, it was like I looked in a mirror and I... I saw somebody worth saving, um, or that I wanted to at least try real hard and save.
嗯…你知道,沒有人……沒人救了我。
Um... You know, nobody... Nobody saved me.
他說"你只管工作"
And he goes, "you just work."
當他告訴我這些時，我第一次見到他時就相信了。
When he told me that, I bought into it when I first met him.
隨著我對他了解的加深，我意識到這一點。
And then as I got to know him more, I realized it jumped.
成癮嚇了一跳。
The addiction jumped.
當他投入某件事時，他完全投入。
When he threw himself into something, he threw himself completely.
柔術很好，因為他變得超級健康。
Jujitsu was a good one because he got super healthy.
他看起來很好。他停止吸煙。
He looked great. He stopped smoking.
他感到精力充沛。
He felt energized.
他感覺強大。
He felt powerful.
哦。
Oh.
中止。
Abort.
我從58歲開始。
I started at 58.
我妻子是一個相當高水平的競爭者，嗯，訓練每一個…比你的水平高?
My wife is a fairly high-level competitor and, uh, trains every... Higher level than you are?
遠遠超出了我的想象。-是的。
W-way, way beyond - where I'll ever be. - Yeah.
奧塔維亞想殺死任何襲擊他們女兒的人。
Ottavia wanted to be able to kill anyone who came at their daughter.
這就是那個家庭最初對柔術感興趣的原因，對托尼來說，癡迷一段時間是件好事。
So that's where the initial jujitsu interest in that family came from, and it was a good thing for Tony to be obsessed with for a while.
在壓力下解決問題的這一方面對他很有吸引力。
There is this aspect of problem-solving under pressure that it was really appealing to him.
一步結束了!
Step over!
但是任何學柔術的人都會變得，讓人無法接近。
But anyone who gets into jujitsu becomes, like, impossible to be around.
我知道,因為……從經驗。
I know because... From experience.
在某種程度上，你會想，“伙計，別再談他媽的柔道了。”
At a certain point, you're like, "dude, come on, stop talking about fucking jujitsu."
我對柔術一竅不通。
I don't know anything about jujitsu.
我不能跟你談這個話題，但我已經跟你談了150小時的柔術了。
Like, I can't have this conversation, and yet I'm on like hour 150 talking to you about jujitsu.
我是說，他的注意力和專注力非常強，但總是有時間限制的。
I mean, his attention and focus was so strong, but there was always a timeline.
我不認為在他的世界裡有什麼東西是永恆的。
I don't think there was anything that would have lasted forever in his world.
沒有人，沒有地方，沒有東西，沒有興趣。
No person, place, thing, interest.
我得先給你看。
I have to show you first.
我能給你看一次嗎?好吧。
Can-can I show you once? Okay.
然後跳過一個，往下走。
Then you skip one and you go down.
然後你回來…
Then you come back up and...
似乎他一直想要的，就是，田園般的生活，就像，你知道，一個家庭和普通的生活。
It always seemed like what he wanted was, you know, this, uh, idyllic picture of, like, you know, a family and ordinary life.
——沒有。-拜托，是你做的…但當他拿到的時候，我不知道是不是…我不知道。
- No. - Come on, you were doing it... But then when he got it, I don't know if it was... I don't know.
是的。
Yeah.
過了一段時間，也許這已經不夠了。
After a while, maybe that wasn't enough anymore.
你把你的書獻給了家人。
You devoted your book to family.
是的。
Yep.
做普通人的快樂。
The joys of being normal.
現在你已經離開了。
And now you've-you've split.
——是的。-所以我就…你是不是在重新考慮做正常人，或者你的…-我是說，什麼才算正常?
- Yep. - So I just, like... Are you rethinking about being normal - or where's your... - Well, I mean, what is normal?
我想，美國家庭是什麼樣的?
I think, you know, what does the American family look like?
我一年有250天在旅行。
I mean, I travel 250 days a year.
你知道，我還能有多正常嗎?
You know, how normal could I ever hope to be?
托尼和我幾乎是分開住在同一個屋簷下…很長一段時間了。
Tony and I had been pretty much living separate under the same roof for... For quite some time.
即使我們不是夫妻，我們還是很好的朋友我們的關注點是阿麗亞娜。
You know, even if we didn't work out as a married couple, you know, we're still really good friends and our focus was ariane.
那種浪漫的愛情在他開始強烈的旅行後就消失了，然後我們就不能跟著他了。
That romantic love kind of dissipated after he started traveling so intensely, and then we couldn't follow him.
它每五年開一次花。
It flowers once every five years.
這是所有。
That's all.
我會在它再次開花前回來的。
I'll be back before it flowers again.
穿過我的心。
Cross my heart.
他會很絕望。
He was devastated.
他正在失去他的本壘。
He was losing his home base.
這讓他變得非常脆弱。
And it left him incredibly vulnerable.
我想托尼確實是自責。
I think Tony did blame himself.
我想這也讓他懷疑自己是否可愛。
And I think it also left him wondering whether or not he was lovable.
是一個人待在一個很糟糕的地方更糟糕呢，還是一個很好的地方卻不能和任何人分享?
Is it worse to be some place awful when you're by yourself or some place really nice that you can't share with anyone?
我的意思是，我有一封他發給我的郵件，讓我很困擾，很直接…你知道，突然之間。
I mean, I have an email that he sent me that-that haunts me that was just straight-up... You know, out of the blue.
“大衛，問這個問題太瘋狂了……”
"David, this is a crazy thing to ask..."
〞...但我很好奇，現在我的生活一團糟。”
"...but I'm curious and my life is sort of shit now."
“你成功了，我也成功了。
"You are successful and I am successful.
“我想知道:
"And I'm wondering:
你快樂嗎?”
Are you happy?"
我知道寫那封郵件對他來說有多難。
I know how hard that must've been for him to even write that email.
去找一個人然後說"嘿，伙計，我做得不好"
To-to reach out to someone and be like, "hey, man, I'm not doing well."
他與孩子和奧塔維亞生活的那個時代……我認為這是對他軌跡的一種干擾。
The era of his life with his child and ottavia... I think it was sort of an interruption of his trajectory.
在過去的兩年裡他改變了方向嗎?
Did he change course in the last two years?
不，他回到了正軌，但這並不是最好的軌道。
No, he got back on track, which was not the greatest track.
你好,托尼。你好嗎?
Hi, Tony. How are you?
我一切都好。在這裡嗎?
I'm all right. Here?
突出。好。
Outstanding. Good.
太棒了。
That's awesome.
我甚至還帶來了一張紙條……我把筆記。
I even brought a note... I took notes.
我在想我所有的…所有的疾病和問題。
I was thinking of all my... All of my ailments and problems.
自從我…我那時還是個青少年。
I haven't done this since I was, um... Uh, I was a teenager.
我父母發現我吸毒，作為交易的一部分，我去看了心理醫生。
My parents caught me with drugs, and as part of the deal, I saw a therapist briefly.
你對此有何感想?
And what did you feel about it?
這是沒辦法讓人筋疲力盡。
It's-it's exhausting.
我是說，我確實有點躁狂的性格。
I mean, I do tend to have a sort of a manic personality.
一切都進行得非常非常順利或者並不順利。
Everything is going really, really great or it's not going great.
它隨時都可能發生。這是隨機的。
It can happen at any time. It's a random thing.
前一分鍾我還好一切都很順利然後突然就…一件小事讓我很生氣，然後我發現自己，呃，你知道，越來越多地，呃，在想……
One minute, I'm okay, everything's going all right, and then suddenly it's... One little thing just sort of sets me off, and then I find myself, uh, you know, increasingly, uh, thinking...
我想，我想，我想，我想，我想傷害別人或自己的瞬間幻想。
I do, I do, I do, I think about, like, momentary fantasies of harming other people or myself.
就像我想殺了人或者掐死他們或者扭斷他們的胳膊。
Like I want to kill somebody or choke them or break their arms.
這事我想了很多。
Uh, I think about that a lot.
我想要更快樂。
I'd like to be happier.
我希望能更冷靜一些。
I'd like to be able to be calmer.
我希望能放松一下。
I'd like to be able to relax.
我希望能夠，你知道，看著窗外說，“耶，生活很美好。”
I'd like to be able to, you know, look out the window and say, "yay, life is good."
-你不喜歡?——沒有。
- And you don't? - No.
從來沒有嗎?
Never?
也許這裡幾秒鍾，那裡幾秒鍾。
Uh, maybe a few seconds here and there.
在你的生命中有一條線是孤獨的或者感覺像"我想殺了某人"
There is a line during your life of loneliness or-or feeling like "I want to kill somebody."
我覺得你應該開始思考"你真的想改變什麼嗎"
I think that maybe you should start thinking, "do you really want to change anything?"
你真的想改變你的感覺嗎?
Do you really want to-to change the way you feel?
我懷疑已經太遲了。
I suspect it's too late.
我可以安定下來
□ I can settle down □
□做得很好□
□ and be doing just fine □
□直到我聽到一輛舊火車的聲音……□
□ till I hear an old train... □
我喜歡這輛車。
I love this car.
我羨慕你的車。
I'm having car envy.
我們都在不停地談論電影中的消失點。
We were both, like, constantly talking about that movie vanishing point.
他也喜歡快車。
He liked fast cars, as well.
我喜歡快車。
I love fast cars.
然後我們成了多年的筆友，什麼都聊。
And then we became pen pals really for years and, um, talked about everything.
他的整個人格就是一個探索者。
His whole entire personality was that of a searcher.
我只知道他肯定在找什麼東西，而且…但你要明白
I just know that he was definitely searching for something, and-and... □ But you gotta understand □
這對他來說是一種痛苦。
it was kind of agony for him.
當主造我的時候
□ When the lord made me □
□他造了一個漫步的人…□
□ he made a ramblin' man... □
就是這種無情的本能把好事搞砸了。
It's this relentless instinct to fuck up a good thing.
我認為這是電視上的人，寫作的人，烹飪的人都會分享的東西。
I think it's something that people on TV, people who write, people who cook, share.
給予和接受愛的困難…他們只是不知道該怎麼做。
This difficulty in giving love and receiving love... They just don't quite know how to do it.
很多人都很喜歡他。
A lot of people loved him a lot.
我不知道他信不信。
I don't know if he believed it.
你覺得呢?
So, what do you think?
我的意思是，從形而上學的角度來說，當你回顧你的一生…-是的。
I mean, in a metaphysical way, - when you look back on your life... - Yeah.
對我來說，我總是感到有點不安，就像……你覺得自己受的苦還不夠多——或者你做的還不夠多……-這他媽是怎麼回事?
For me, I always feel this little unease, like, you know... You feel you haven't suffered enough yet - or you haven't done enough... - How the fuck did this happen?
是的。——你知道嗎?
- Or yeah. - You know?
-這是怎麼發生的?——沒有。
- How-how'd this happen, you know? - No.
不,我知道。
No, I know.
我還是很好奇。
I'm still curious.
你看起來是個很好奇的人。
You seem like a curious person.
-這是我唯一的美德。——你……那就這樣吧。
- It's my only virtue. - You're... there you go.
好吧。
All right.
好奇是一件好事。
Curious is a good thing to be.
給你的生活…什麼讓你興奮?
Given your life... What thrills you?
現在是什麼讓你這麼激動?
What just thrills the shit out of you now?
呃，這很尷尬，但真的很尷尬。。。被愛，並真正感激那些給予我愛的人。
Uh, this is very embarrassing, but... it's really embar... Being loved and actually appreciating the people that are giving that to me.
你們准備好了，攝像機就開始了。——好的。
Whenever you guys are ready, - the cameras are rolling. - All right.
我們准備好了。
We're ready to go.
好了，你起來了?
All right, you're up?
那麼，我們說到哪兒了?
So, uh, where are we?
但是不要提到那個地方的名字。
But don't mention the name of the place.
-我是說，把餐巾翻過來…——沒有。為什麼?
- I mean, turning the napkin over... - No. Why?
好吧,我們不…你不會想把這裡炸了的。
Well, we don't... you don't want to blow this place up.
我才不管呢。
I don't give a shit.
你在這吃了多久了?
I mean, you've been eating here for how long?
從我還是個孩子的時候。
Since I was a, since I was a kid.
所以你來這裡看到的只有美國人?
So you would come in here and see nothing but Americans?
除了嗎?
Nothing but?
——除了?——好吧,是的。
- Nothing but? - Well, yeah.
-我是說，只是一群…-是的，這樣就沒人敢打我了。
- I mean, just an army of... - Well, yes, so nobody busts my balls.
好吧,。我們在…所以，放棄吧。
Okay, then. We are at the... So, giving up on that.
好吧。好了。
Okay. There we go.
你們家幾代人都是電影制作人?
H-How many generations of filmmakers in your family?
嗯,很多。
Mm, a lot.
歡呼。
Cheers.
當托尼遇到亞西亞時，他說，“她是最棒的。”天啊，她太棒了。”
When Tony met Asia, he's like, "she's the best. Oh, my god, she's so great."
你知道，就像你在高中的時候你第一次跟人上床什麼的。
You know, and, like, when you were in high school and you got laid for the first time or something.
你知道，當生活像電影一樣的時候我最開心。
You know, I'm happiest when life is kind of like a film.
所以你在幻想中很快樂。
So, y-you're happy in the illusion.
-因為電影是幻覺。——是的。
- 'Cause film is an illusion. - Yes.
是的,我是。
Yeah, I am.
不,我也是。我理解你。
No, me, too. I-I understand you.
他和她在一起似乎很幸福。
He seemed really happy with her.
我當時想，他找到了他想要的人。
You know, I was like, well, he found someone he wants to be with.
我為他感到高興。
You know, I'm happy for him.
他告訴我，她對他們的關系很沒有安全感，所以他就叫我不要再把我們的照片發到社交媒體上。
He told me that she was very insecure about their relationship, so he just asked me to stop posting pictures of us on social media.
我覺得他真的認為他在做正確的事確保他愛的人有安全感。
And-and I think he really thought he was doing the right thing to make sure that the person he loved felt secure.
這是正常的沖動嗎?
Is that a normal urge?
——對人類?-我想做正常人?
- For humans? - I want to be normal?
我想和其他人一樣嗎?
I want to be like everybody else?
當我還是個孩子的時候，我有點想和其他人一樣，至少有一段時間。
I kind of wanted to be like everybody else when I was a kid, at least for a while.
我不明白為什麼我不能。
I-I didn't understand why I couldn't be.
我認為當人們有歸屬感時，他們會更快樂。
I think people are happier when they feel like they belong somewhere.
-我只是…-這就是為什麼我從來沒有快樂過，因為我覺得我從來沒有歸屬感。
- I just, i-i... - That's why I'm never happy because I feel I never belong.
我知道她是誰，但他從不提她的名字。
I knew who she was, but he never would use her name.
他會在所有郵件裡說"瘋狂的意大利女演員"
He would say "crazy Italian actress" in all the emails.
我只知道他給我寫過幾次信說結局會非常非常糟糕，那是很久以前的事了。
All I know is that he wrote to me a few times and said that it was gonna end very, very badly, and that was way back.
嗯，他知道。
Um, he knew it.
哦!
Oh!
我帶你去最好的地方。
I bring you to the best places.
他媽的米其林。
Fuck michelin.
米其林嗎?
Michelin?
他的上一段感情，我想當你審視它的時候，就不會那麼驚訝了。
His last relationship, I guess when you look at it, it's not that surprising.
在很多方面，它從一開始就給人一種橢圓的感覺。
In many ways, it feels elliptical from the-the very beginning.
現在，你們可能會問，“這和食物有什麼關系?”我才不知道呢。
Now, some of you might ask, "how is this food-related?" Fuck if I know.
我想如果我的頭骨被石頭砸碎了，我的一部分就會成為食物鏈的一部分。
I guess if I crushed my skull on a rock, parts of me will become part of the food chain.
這是一個，在它的中心，嗯，有極端。
It was one that had, at its center, um, extremes.
就好像他感覺不到中間地帶。
It's as if he can't feel in the mid-zone.
生活就是要找到一個值得一跳的懸崖。
You know, life is about finding a cliff worth jumping off.
我覺得他好像在說"我要去找些野性的東西"
I felt he was like, "I'm gonna look for something feral and wild."
也許這與年齡有關，突然發現自己很孤單。
Perhaps that is something to do with age and all of a sudden finding yourself alone.
這個叫做，嗯…-你們起來了嗎?-你為什麼拍我?
This is called, um... - Are you guys up? - Why are you filming me?
這就叫做“我們的狼女之花”。
This is called "our wolf lady of the wolf flowers."
啊,太好了。
Ah, that's great.
我床上有個叫約翰·盧瑞的。
You know, I have a-a John lurie over my bed.
我看到了。不，是你發的。
I saw. No, you posted it.
你發這個帖子很好。
That was nice that you posted that.
不，我很喜歡。這讓我非常非常高興。
No, I love it. It makes me very, very happy.
——不是嗎?-是的。
- Does it? - Yes, it does.
所以他有黑色幽默。
So he had a dark sense of humor.
他不是埃德加·愛倫·坡。你懂我的意思嗎?他……他周圍有很多光。
He wasn't Edgar Allan poe. You know what I mean? He... There was a lot of light around him.
確實是。
There really was.
帶來另一個。
Bring another one.
不。我的意思是，尤其是，比如，我離開了，然後我回來——然後我走進我的房間……-就是這個，對，對。
No. I mean, especially, like, I'm away and I come back - and I walk into my room... - There it is, yeah, yeah.
我感覺……房間的震動頻率讓我感到舒適和快樂。
I-It feels... The room vibrates at a frequency that makes me comfortable and-and happy.
那很酷。
That's cool.
謝謝你！雞蛋，完美的食物。
Thank you. Eggs, the perfect food.
-謝謝，先生-吃吧
- Thank you, sir. - Eat that.
我們本來要吃午飯的。
We were supposed to have lunch.
我說:“我想去一個安靜的地方，沒有人認識我們。”
And I said, "I want to go somewhere quiet where nobody knows us."
他突然停了下來，說:“我開始有廣場恐懼症了。”
And he just sort of stopped in his tracks and said, "I'm becoming agoraphobic."
然後我看到他臉上的痛苦。
And then I saw the pain in his face.
也許他需要一段時間遠離這一切反思一下然後再重新開始?
Maybe he needed some time away from it all to reflect a minute and then start again kind of thing, you know?
我不…他好像要去做別的事了。
I don't... It seemed like he was about to go on to something else.
他的生命開始變得越來越渺小。
His life started to feel smaller and smaller.
他不能去那麼多地方。
He couldn't go as many places.
他不可能經常出現在公眾場合。
He couldn't be out in public as much.
我能看見他逐漸消瘦下去。
I could see him whittle away.
所以，像阿拉伯沙漠的空區這樣的地方開始真正引起他的共鳴。
So, places like the empty quarter of the arabian desert started to really resonate for him.
坐在世界上最大的沙漠邊緣，凝視著它……感覺這是比他更重要的事而不是關於他的。
To just sit on the edge of the largest sand desert in the world and stare out into it... feeling like it's something that's bigger than him and not about him.
他經常說，在一個理想的世界裡，他不會出現在劇中。
He often talked about how, in an ideal world, he wouldn't be in the show.
這是他的視角，就像在太空中移動的攝像機，根本看不到他。
Uh, it would be his point of view, like a camera moving through space, without having to see him at all.
“旅行並不總是美好的。”
"Travel isn't always pretty."
“你走開。你學習。”
"You go away. You learn."
“在這個過程中，你會傷痕累累，留下印記，改變自己。”
"You get scarred, marked, changed in the process."
“它甚至會讓你心碎。”
"It even breaks your heart."
他非常緊張，非常疲憊，非常疲憊。
He was very stressed and very weary and very exhausted.
他確實說過要辭職。
He did talk about quitting.
大概是幾年前的事了。
It happened like a couple of years ago.
他約我和克裡斯在酒吧見面。
He asked to see Chris and I at a bar.
非常戲劇化。
It was very dramatic.
他說"我不能再這樣生活了"
He was like, "I can't live my life like this anymore."
“我做的。我受夠了。我受夠你們這些人了。
"I'm done. I'm done with this. I'm done with you people.
“每個樂隊都有結束的時候。
"Every band comes to an end.
我們是時候分手了，各奔東西了。”
It's time for us to break up and go our separate ways."
“你知道，我曾經破壞過一個家庭。
"You know, I've broken one family.
“我正處在另一段我非常在乎的感情中，我想讓它繼續下去。”
"I'm in this other relationship that I care very deeply about and I want to make it work."
莉迪亞看著托尼說:“那就去做吧。”
And Lydia looked at Tony and said, "then go do it.
“去做。
"Go do it.
“別坐在這裡抱怨這件事。
"Don't sit here and talk about it and whine.
“起來走吧。離開。
"Get up and go. Leave.
“搬到意大利，開始工作。
"Move to Italy, set up.
我們會支持你的。我們會成為你的朋友。走吧。”
We will support you. We will be your friend. Go."
“比如，如果你做完了，沒關系。”
"Like, if you're done with this, it's okay."
我不知道。也許他希望我們抓住他，然後說"不，別走。
I don't know. Maybe he was expecting us to, like, grab him and say like, "no, don't go.
這不是結束。我們能做什麼?”
It's not over. What can we do?"
他不能移動。
He couldn't move.
這真的有點悲哀。
It's really kind of sad.
就像"那就他媽的坐下來，我們好好談談"
It's like, "then sit the fuck down and let's talk this thing through."
我們說，“我們會想辦法讓它工作的，你知道，這對你有好處。”
And we said, "we'll figure out a way to make this thing work, you know, so it's good for you."
好吧。我們開始吧。
Okay. Here we go.
“香港。
"Hong Kong.
愛上亞洲……”
To fall in love with Asia..."
嘔,亞洲。
Oof, Asia.
“愛上亞洲是一回事。
"To fall in love with Asia is one thing.
而在亞洲墜入愛河則是另一回事。
"To fall in love in Asia is another.
“這兩種情況都發生在我身上。
"Both have happened to me.
它是禮物，是夢想，是詛咒，是世界上最好的事，最幸福的事，但也是最孤獨的事。
"It's a gift, a dream, a curse, "the best thing, the happiest thing, "yet also the loneliest thing in the world.
“我以前去過香港很多次，但不是這樣的。”
"I've been to Hong Kong many times before, but not like this."
如果我在40歲之前死了，那可能和那次槍擊有關。
If I die before I'm 40 years old, that shoot probably had something to do with it.
在最後一秒，導演生病了。
At the last second, the director gets sick.
我切除了膽囊。
I had my gallbladder removed.
邁克爾的膽囊，我發誓。
Michael's gallbladder, I swear to god.
顯然我不能去，然後托尼馬上就看到了。
So, obviously I can't go, and then Tony immediately, like, sees an in.
他讓所有人都同意，亞洲應該指揮這一行動。
He gets them to all agree that Asia should direct this.
W-Well,好吧。
W-Well, like, okay.
那人…從某種程度上說，在這一邊，這給了他某種，像是，強烈復蘇的創造力。
In-in man... in some ways, on this side, this is giving him some kind of, like, intense resurgence of, like, creative energy.
所以我們就這麼做了。
And so we-we ran with that.
——亞洲?-我想…馬上回來。
- Asia? - I think... Back in one sec.
我們得到的好東西太多了……我知道,但時間太短了。
We're getting too much good stuff... I know, but... in too short a period of time.
讓我們動起來，動起來。是的。
Let's mo... let's move and-and move. Yeah.
我們得到的太多了。
And w-we're getting too much.
就像，我的意思是，在這個時候，對每個人來說，我在想，“別再說那麼多好東西了。”
It's like, I mean, at this point, it's like, to everybody, I'm thinking, "stop saying so much great stuff."
-我的天啊。——所以快樂。
- Oh, my god. - So happy.
食物准備好了。
Food's ready.
亞西亞，食物准備好了。
Asia, the food's ready.
就好像我們花了這麼多年來塑造和創造這個東西，突然之間，就被扔出了窗外，一切都變了。
It seemed like so many years of us shaping and creating this thing, all of a sudden, was thrown out the window, and it was just, you know, anything goes.
那麼你的…你的希望是什麼?
So what is your... what is your hope?
你希望發生什麼事情來改變你的處境?
What do you hope will happen to change your situation?
說實話，我不太喜歡希望。
To-to be honest, um, I'm not big fan of hope.
嗯,希望是……等一下。
Um, hope is... Hold on one second.
我重置。
Let me reset.
在這兩個尋求庇護者感人的場景中，我們停下來…我握著我的手還是握著我的思想?
In the middle of this heartfelt scene with these two asylum seekers, we're stopping... I hold my hand or h-hold the thought?
告訴他們要堅持自己的想法，重做一遍，就像我們在拍電影一樣。
And telling them to hold their thought and to, like, redo it, as if we're filming a movie or something.
-再加一個——三個。
- Uh, add one. - Three.
35毫…呃,厘米。
35 milli... uh, centimeters.
你知道，打破自然的，發自內心的對話，這不是容易的對話，他永遠不會這樣做。
You know, breaking the natural, heartfelt conversations that are not easy conversations to have, he would have never, ever done that.
我們走吧。准備好了。
Let's go. Ready to go.
對不起，再來一次。
I'm sorry, do it again.
亞洲嗎?
Asia?
在香港發生的事情…聽。
What happened in Hong Kong was... listen.
我們只是想幫我們的朋友。
We-we were trying to help our friend.
如果這意味著…嗯…做……是的。
And if that meant... Um... Doing... yeah.
在我一生中所做的一切中，這可能是職業生涯中最精彩的部分。
Of everything I've done in my life, this was probably the professional highlight.
導演亞西亞·阿基多和攝影導演克裡斯托弗·道爾之間……-你要給我一台相機?地獄——是的。
Between, uh, Asia argento as the director and Christopher Doyle as the director of photography... - You're gonna give me a camera? - Hell yeah.
我們真的做了一些特別的事情。
We really did something special.
好了，開始抽大麻吧。
All right, proceed to smoke weed.
我覺得我很開心。
I think I'm happy.
為什麼?這是如此平靜?
Why? It's so peaceful?
是的。
Yeah.
順便說一句，這是電影中最好的鏡頭。
This is the best shot in the movie, by the way.
哇，太他媽漂亮了。
Wow, this is fucking beautiful.
等待。
Wait.
順便說一句，我在節目上不怎麼笑，但我現在在笑。
I don't smile a lot on this show, by the way, but I'm smiling now.
我真想殺了你們。
I want to shoot you guys.
跟我們說說你的團隊。
So, tell us about your team.
扎克,12年的老兵。
Zach, 12-year veteran.
扎克把不為人知的部分制作成了最美的電視節目之一。
Zach had made parts unknown one of the most beautiful shows on television.
托尼對扎克的崇拜讓人興奮不已。
Tony's admiration for Zach was just kind of mind-blowing.
在香港，扎克與亞洲人對拍攝內容有不同的看法。
In Hong Kong, Zach had a differing opinion from Asia on what they were shooting.
盡管他有著深厚的歷史、愛和友誼，他還是離開了。
And despite having a huge history and love and friendship, he was gone.
托尼炒了扎克，這是一個巨大的危險信號，因為這就像，如果他要對像他這樣的人這麼做，我是說，任何核心圈子裡的人基本上都是，你知道的，被拋棄的。
When Tony fired Zach, it was a huge red flag, because it was like, if he's gonna do that to someone like him, I mean, anyone on the inner circle is essentially, you know, disposable.
歡呼。
Cheers.
去年發生了一件非常瘋狂的事，高潮非常非常高。
There was a very sort of manic nature to what was going on in that last year, where the highs were very, very high.
低潮非常丑陋。
And the lows were very ugly.
他已經不是原來的他了。
He was not the same person.
有些東西變了，變得很重。
Something changed and became really heavy.
但在某個時候，他開始去接受治療，我想，“我可以退一步。
But he started going to therapy at a certain point, and I thought, "I can take a step back.
“我不用，你知道的，總是那麼擔心他。”
"I don't have to be, like, you know, always so, uh, worried about him."
,嗯…
And, uh...
我覺得這是一件我永遠都會覺得…我應該多盯著他的，你知道嗎?
And I feel like that's something that I will always, you know, felt like... I should have kept an eye on him more, you know?
他來的越來越少了。
He came by less and less.
幸運的話，我們每個月都能見到他一次。
And we would see him once a month, if we were lucky.
你知道嗎，他對我說了些屁話，真的…真他媽氣死我了。
You know, he said some shit to me that was really... Fucking pissed me off.
嗯…你知道，去他媽的。
Um... You know, fuck it.
托尼說過我永遠不會成為一個好爸爸。
You know, Tony said I would never be a good dad.
這該死的傷害。
That fucking hurt.
我知道他不是故意的，但是…
And I know he wasn't trying to be mean, but...
-他是在預測嗎?-是的。
- Was he projecting? - Yeah.
他當然是在預測。
Of course he was projecting.
他盡了一切努力去做一個父親。
He did everything he could to be the... a dad.
我想這傷透了他的心因為他沒能成為他想要的那種父親，那種浪漫的父親。
I think it broke his heart that he couldn't be the fucking dad he thought he could be, the romantic version of a dad.
他對生活，對任何事，對家庭，對整個生活都是如此的浪漫。
He was such a romantic about life, about anything, about families, about life as a whole.
生活是一種浪漫的想法，現實永遠不會完全符合他的想象。
Life was a romantic idea, and reality was never gonna live up to exactly how he pictured it.
他總是讓自己失望。
He was always gonna sort of set himself up for disappointment.
哇。
Wow.
有一種我不習慣的巨大的感覺。
There's a sense of, um, vastness that I'm not used to.
這讓你想起了你的牛仔電影嗎?
Does this remind you of your cowboy movies?
-有一點-是的。
- Uh, a little bit. - Yeah.
是的，想要復仇的孤軍奮戰的槍手在那邊的勝算不大。
Yes, the lone gunman out for vengeance would be riding in a long shot over there.
在那一刻，我認為他認為他與亞洲的關系可以為他提供一個答案。
At that point, I think he thought his relationship with Asia could provide him with an answer.
——但無論如何……-你說得對，你說得對。
- But anyway... - You're right, you're right.
你知道嗎?他對她的愛是完全純潔、安全、有益和支持的。
You know? His love for her was completely pure and safe and helpful and supportive.
這正是他想從她身上得到的。
Which is essentially what he was looking for from her.
我認為托尼認為贏得她信任的方法就是全心全意地投入。
And I think that Tony concluded that the way to earn her trust was just to go in with his whole heart.
有請安東尼·波登!
Please welcome Anthony bourdain!
這是比較痛苦的一種。
One of the more painful and-and.
我覺得你人生中有趣的經歷發生在最近的"我也是"運動中。
I-I would think interesting journeys you've taken on your life happened just very recently with regards to the me too movement.
我開始談論這件事是出於一種真正的憤怒。
I started speaking about it out of a sense of real rage.
我是說，我想說我…我到達……在某種程度上，我總是很開明，或者說我是一個積極分子或有道德的人。
I mean, I'd like to say that I'm... I-I arrived at... I was always enlightened in some way or that I am an activist or virtuous.
但事實上，你知道的，我必須對自己誠實。
But, in fact, uh, you know, I have to be honest with myself.
我遇到了一位非凡的女性，她有一個非凡而痛苦的故事。
I met one extraordinary woman with an extraordinary and painful story.
突然間就有私人恩怨了。
Uh, suddenly it was personal.
我想很多人都很驚訝。
I think it surprised a lot of people.
他從來沒有真正想過要為一個事業而堅持自己的立場。
He had never really wanted to stick himself out there for a cause.
但托尼說"我要挺身而出"
But Tony was like, "I'm going to make a stand."
一顆核彈就要落在我最大的敵人身上了。
A nuclear bomb is gonna fall on one of my worst enemies.
所有人都在為他辯護，但現在他要完蛋了。
Everybody's been defending him, but now he's going fucking down.
他要完蛋了。
He's going down big-fucking-time.
1997年，我在戛納被哈維·溫斯坦強奸了。
In 1997, I was raped by Harvey weinstein here at cannes.
即使今晚，坐在你們中間，仍有一些人必須為他們對婦女的行為負責。
And even tonight, sitting among you, there are those who still have to be held accountable for their conduct against women.
阿基多後來在Instagram上發布了這張照片，她的拳頭在空中，法語翻譯的標題是，“婦女之戰仍在繼續。”
Argento later posting this photo on Instagram with her fist in the air, the caption in French translated, "the battle of women continues."
亞洲剛剛從戛納過來。
Asia had just come from cannes.
然後我們在烏菲茲畫廊看荷洛芬的斬首，也就是對強奸她的人的斬首，就發生在溫斯坦被捕的那天。
And then we're in the uffizi gallery looking at the beheading of holofernes, which is literally the beheading of her rapist, and it's happening the day that weinstein gets arrested.
韋恩斯坦多次否認所有指控。
Weinstein has repeatedly denied all allegations.
這是非凡的。
It was extraordinary.
大家都把美杜莎看作是腦袋裡有蛇的邪惡女人的象征，但是，她是強奸受害者。
Everybody takes medusa as the symbol of the evil woman with snakes in her head, but, uh, she was, uh, a rape victim.
她必須保護自己。
And she had to protect herself.
你知道嗎，那些惹怒別人的有權勢又麻煩的女人總是被畫成美杜莎。
You know, powerful, inconvenient women who piss people off are inevitably caricatured as medusa.
是的。
Yeah.
我說下一個。
I'm-I'm next.
我本來不想說的。
I wasn't gonna say it.
-這只是時間問題。——嗯。
- It's only a matter of time. - Hmm.
這是不可思議的。
It's incredible.
我也是!
Me too!
我們的故事是真的!
Our stories are true!
我們說我也是!
We say me too!
我是說，一開始他很高尚，你知道嗎?
I mean, at first it was, like, very noble of him, you know?
這是一個很好的理由。
And it was a good cause.
但後來他成了……是的，他對它很著迷。
But then he became... Yeah, he became obsessed with it.
你用一種很多人不會用的方式來談論它。
You're talking about it in a way that many people wouldn't.
如果一個朋友在五年前說了些什麼，可能會……可能也會冒犯到我，因為他會，把他們從他的生活中趕出去。
To the point where if a friend said something five years ago that would maybe... Might be offensive to the me too cause, he would just, like, cut them out of his life.
在這個問題上，我幾乎是冷酷無情的。——正確的。
I'm pretty much ming the merciless - on this issue right now. - Right.
朋友和創意伙伴……他沒跟他們商量就把他們扔到車底下了。
Friends and creative partners... He threw them under the bus without any sort of consultation or anything.
我的意思是，在他生命的那個階段並沒有太多的細微差別。
I mean, there was not much nuance when it got to that point of his life.
我看到的是他把一個終生上癮的人格變成了另一個人。
What I saw was him turn what was a lifelong addictive personality to another person.
這是非常危險的。
And that was extremely dangerous.
他表現得就像個孩子，他不明白如果你不停地堆積，堆積，堆積，堆積，堆積會把人趕走的。
He was acting like a kid who didn't understand that you're gonna drive someone away if you just pile on and pile on and pile on.
——是的。但是我……-真的，你做過的十大最熱門的事情是在羅馬停車。
- Yes. But-but what I... - Really, the top ten hottest things you've ever done is park in Rome.
什麼,就像……她說"你現在可以停在這裡" "但一小時後你就不能停在這裡了"-是的。
What, like... she was like, "you could park here now, - "but in an hour you can't park here." - Yeah.
“我們現在可以脫身了。”
"We can get away with this now."
我想"這真是太他媽酷了"
I thought, "this is the fucking coolest thing."
他一直在說她停車的能力。
He won't stop fucking talking about her ability to park.
就像"你真是個好帕克。
It's like, "you're such a good Parker.
“你把車停得真好。你停得真好。
"Y-You park so well. You park so well.
你的平行泊車技術真好。”
You parallel park so well."
她說"伙計，我可不想因為我的停車技術而出名"
And she's like, "dude, I don't want to be known for my parking skills."
就像，你可以看到她在退縮，而他就是不肯停下來。
Like, you can see her pulling back, and he just won't stop.
我們玩得很開心。
We're having so much fun.
完成了。
Done.
真是天才，兄弟。
And it was genius, bro.
我跟你說，奧斯卡上見。
I'm telling you, see you at the oscars, yo.
和他說再見是我見過他最開心的事。
Saying goodbye to him is the happiest I felt like I had ever seen him.
巨大的擁抱。
Huge hugs.
他說:“我愛你。”
He was like, "I love you."
“我喜歡和你一起工作。我們還有很長的路要走。
"I love working with you. We got years ahead of us.
我很期待。”
I'm looking forward to it."
你不希望他的遺產給人的印象是…就像這樣……
You don't want his legacy to come off as, like, somebody who... Succumbed to, like, this...
黑暗。
darkness.
那不是他。
That wasn't him.
他創造了一件非常重要的東西。
Like, he created something that was so important.
我希望……那真的需要…那是他一生的遺產。
And I want... that really needs to be, like... That is the legacy of his life.
而不是他最後做的蠢事。
Not this stupid bullshit act that he did at the end.
我們如何接受……發生了什麼事?
How do we come to terms with... what happened?
嗯。這是我不會說的。
Hmm. That's something I don't speak about.
法國發生了什麼。
What happened in France.
從哪裡開始呢?
Um, where to start?
我們的場景和拍攝方式……你知道，就像托尼和埃裡克。
The kind of scenes that we had and what kind of shoot it was... You know, it was, like, Tony and Eric.
輕松,有趣。
Lighthearted, funny.
嗯…哇。哇。
Um... Wow. Wow.
——聽著,男人。聽。-你嘲笑我。
- Listen, man. Listen. - And you mocked me.
我們大概有四天了。
We're probably like four days in.
托尼來了，他剛…很明顯只是有點生氣。
Tony arrives, and he is just... Palpably sort of like just angry.
和…場景有點…它需要一個黑暗的轉折。
And... The scene sort of... It takes a dark turn.
他們說要死了，被熱狗噎死之類的。
Uh, they're talking about dying, choking on a hot dog or something like that.
他回過頭來看著我，我們眼神交流。
He kind of looks back at me, and we kind of make eye contact.
在我的記憶裡，它非常絕望。
In-in my memory now, it's very desperate.
我給海倫打了電話，一份關於亞洲和另一個人的小報出來了。
I called Helen, and this tabloid shit's come out about Asia and this other person.
托尼又走到陽台上，望著山谷，他好像在抽煙，有點孤單。
Tony goes over to this balcony again, looking over this valley, and he's, like, smoking, and he's kind of alone.
我走到那裡，然後說，嘿，伙計，你還好嗎?
I go out there, and I'm like, "hey, man, how are you doing?
“你知道，這是不是，就像……這些是小報的人嗎，"在耍你們嗎?
"You know, is this just, like... Are these just tabloid people, "like, fucking with you guys?
比如，你知道……發生了什麼?”
Like how, you know... What's happening?"
然後，他停頓了一下……然後他就說"小心點"
And then, like, he pauses... and he just says, "a little fucking discretion."
對吧?我就想"嘿，伙計，我只是…"
Right? And I was like, "hey, man, I'm just..."
他說"不，伙計，不是你"
He's like, "no, man, not you."
就像，“我他媽的不想處理這個……這些該死的……”
It's like, "I don't want to have to fucking deal with this... these fucking..."
你知道，他說的是亞洲。
You know, he's talking about Asia.
他甚至連看都不看我一眼。
He didn't even look at me.
你知道，他就像，就像，你知道，就像，就像，就像，就像，就像"操"
You know, he's just kind of, like, just, you know, smoking and just sort of looking out and just like, "fuck."
我真希望當時我能多跟他說點什麼。
I wish I had said more to him in that moment.
你知道，托尼有很長一段時間都不好。
You know, Tony hasn't been all right for a long time.
他開玩笑說要結束自己的生命…他一直在追那鬼東西。
The amount that he joked about the end of his life and... He's been chasing that shit forever.
薯片不新鮮。
Potato chips are stale.
現在好沮喪，我想自殺。
So depressed right now, I feel like killing myself.
他是個該死的跑步者。
He's a fucking runner.
我是說，他跑了很長時間，但你不會戰勝疼痛的。
I mean, he ran for a long time, but you're not gonna outsmart pain.
我很確定那根桿子能支撐我的體重。
I'm pretty sure that pole will support my body weight.
——什麼?-如果我上吊的話。
- What? - If I fucking hang myself.
我想很多人都會想到它，就像，因為他知道怎麼做……我是說，我不知道。
I think it pops into a lot of people's heads, and it's just like, since he knew how to do it... I mean, I don't know.
首先，他是個講故事的人。
He's a storyteller for one thing.
一個講故事的人怎麼能不留下字條就結帳呢?
How does a storyteller check out without leaving a note?
但我覺得，在某種程度上，他會寫下他的結局，他也確實這麼做了。
But I think, in some regard, he was gonna write his end, which is what he did.
如果你看他在Instagram上的最後一個故事，他播放了70年代電影《暴力城市》的主題曲。
If you look at his last Instagram story, he played the title sequence music from this '70s film violent city.
如果你看過這部電影，你就會知道電影的開頭是一系列狗仔隊對這對夫婦的照片。
And if you've seen the film, you know that the beginning is a series of paparazzi photos of this couple.
我是說，這是一部復仇電影。
I mean, it's a revenge film.
講的是一個背叛他的女人他想要復仇。
It's about this woman who betrays him and him seeking revenge.
我是說，都在那兒。
I mean, it's-it's all there.
我很謹慎地去責怪那個女人，就像，你知道的…或者責怪情人或丈夫。
I'm very cautious to be like, uh, blame the woman for, like, you know... Or blame the lover or blame the husband.
你知道嗎，托尼自殺了。
You know, Tony killed himself.
托尼做了。
Tony did it.
我哥哥自殺了。
My brother committed suicide.
我覺得如果當時有人進過他的房間，那就可能是謀殺而不是自殺。
I think if somebody else had been in his room, it might've been a murder and not a suicide.
我覺得他只是暴怒了這是唯一的出路。
I think he was just in an explosive anger and-and this was the only way out.
當你選擇上吊時，這是一種折磨。
When you choose to hang yourself, it's a torture.
自我折磨。
Self-imposed torture.
如果他喝醉了，就容易理解多了。
If he was fucking drunk, it'd be a lot easier to understand.
毒理學報告顯示他是清白的，清醒的。
The toxicology report was he's clean and sober.
我認為這是一個明確的決定。
I think it was a clear decision.
這只是一時的疏忽，我認為他沒有權衡利弊。
It was a momentary lapse, and I don't think he weighed the pros and cons.
如果他能挺過那晚，你知道嗎?
If he had just made it through that night, you know?
我們如此努力地去理解它，因為我們認為如果我們能理解它，我們就會接受它。
We're trying so hard to understand, because we think if we can understand it, then we'll be okay with it.
事實是，不，我想我們還不知道。
And the fact of the matter is, no, I don't think we get to know.
我們不知道。
We don't get to know.
這是一個很難回答的問題。
That's tough.
我不知道他現在在哪，但是…他讓我失望了。
Well, I don't know where he is right now, but... He let me down.
他……
He...
我不認為他殘忍，你知道嗎?
I don't think he was cruel, you know?
這是一種殘忍的行為。
And there's, like, a cruelty to that.
每個人都該怎麼做?
What the hell is everyone supposed to do?
他自殺已經兩年多了，但我仍然有各種各樣的情緒。
It's been over two years since he took his own life, and I still experience a range of emotions.
嗯…
Um...
神。
God.
這就像……他死後我就沒剪過頭發。
It's like... I haven't fucking cut my hair since he died.
喜歡,我……我只是想他了。
Like, i-i... I just miss him.
我想念一個朋友，一個親愛的朋友。
I miss a friend, a dear friend.
我想起了很多我們在一起的快樂時光。
I think about a lot of happy moments we had together.
大多數情況下,是的。
Mostly, yeah.
我在越南，天氣很好。
I was in Vietnam on a beautiful day.
我看了看手機，上面有新聞。
I looked at my phone, and there was the news.
就在那時，我決定永遠搬到越南去。
And, uh, that's when I decided to move to Vietnam for good.
這是……甚至連想都不敢想。
That was the... It was not even a thought.
那扇門打開了，我必須穿過它，開始做一些新的事情。
It was the door opened and I had to go through it and start doing something new.
我聽著這張令我想起他而流淚的唱片。
I was listening to this record that brought me to tears thinking of him.
我的兩個孩子都擁抱了我。
And, um, both my kids sort of embraced me.
我兒子說"托尼是怎麼死的"
My son, he's like, "how did Tony die?"
我說，“呃，我…我們不知道。”
And I was like, "uh, I... we don't know."
對吧?
Right?
大約20秒過去了，他看著我說，“我真的很想知道托尼是怎麼死的。”
About 20 seconds pass, and he looked at me and he's like, "I really would like to know how Tony died."
我跟我七歲的孩子聊了一小時托尼的事。
I have this like hour-long conversation about Tony to my fucking seven-year-old kid.
我說，我覺得托尼，最後，覺得很孤獨，覺得他無法向任何人訴說他內心的痛苦
And I said, "I think Tony, at the end, "felt alone and felt he couldn't talk to anybody about the pain that was going on inside of him."
我說:“你知道，你總有可以傾訴的人。”
And I said, "you know you always have someone to turn to and talk to."
這就是我從中得到的教訓。
That's the lesson in it for me.
只說我受傷了就夠了。
It's plenty to just say I'm hurt.
我已經兩年沒工作了。
I haven't worked for two years now.
快到最後的時候，我們談了一下，我說，"帶著我們的女兒們，減輕她們的負擔"向她們展示這個世界，向她們展示我們是誰，不僅僅是你回家的時候，而是…"
Really close to the end, we talked, and I said, "got to take our girls and lighten the load "and show them the world, show them who we are, not just when you come home, but..."
我們對這個前景都很興奮。
And-and we were both excited about this prospect.
他媽的。
Fuck.
一個,兩個,三個。
One, two, three.
當我生氣的時候，我想到的是留下一個輝煌的…的女兒。
When I get angry is when I think about leaving behind a brilliant... Daughter.
你知道的。
You know.
他很想現在就在她身邊，見到她。
He would have loved to be around now, to see her now.
他會為她感到驕傲的。
He'd be so proud of her.
我很幸運，因為她是我能想到的最好的女兒。
I'm so lucky 'cause she's the best daughter I-I could hope for.
我永遠都很感激，你知道的，托尼把她給了我?
And I will always be grateful that, you know, Tony gave her to me, you know?
我是說，我想這是我最後一次公開談論它，因為我…這不是我想記住的他的樣子。
I mean, I think this is the last time I'll ever talk publicly about it, because I... that's not the way I want to remember him.
我想記住我們在一起時的他，我們做過的所有了不起的事，他是一個了不起的人。
I want to remember him when we were together, all the amazing things that we'd done and the amazing person that he was.
托尼死後，萊斯·哈勒斯餐廳，就成了聖地。
After Tony died, the restaurant, les halles, it just became this shrine.
我們不知道他對那麼多人有那麼重要。
We didn't realize he meant so much to so many people.
“你激勵我走出自己的舒適區，無畏地沉浸在豐富的生活中。”
"You inspired me to get out of my comfort zone and fearlessly immerse myself in the richness of life."
支持工人階級，移民，窮人。
"Advocate for the working classes, "the immigrants, the poor.
這個世界配不上你。”
This world didn't deserve you."
還有一些人留下了詩。
And then a few people left poems.
一個人說:“大家都忘了伊卡洛斯也飛過。”
"One said," everyone forgets that icarus also flew.
“我相信伊卡洛斯並沒有失敗，因為他倒下了，而只是即將結束他的勝利。”
"I believe icarus was not failing as he fell but just coming to the end of his triumph."
你知道，我當時是個憤怒的年輕人。
You know, I was an angry young man.
我,呃…我都忘了我為什麼生氣了，尤其是看著這個。
I-I, uh... I forget what I was angry about, especially looking at this.
我到底為什麼那麼生氣?
What the hell was I so angry about?
這是，你知道…天堂。
This was, you know... paradise.
對不起。
Sorry.
我能說句話嗎?
Can I say something?
看著他在沙灘上散步，很有共鳴，很甜蜜。
To have him walking down a beach, it resonates, it's sweet.
然後我就去了，你知道，我在樓上上廁所，我就像…“他會討厭的。”
And I go, you know, as-as I was upstairs using the restroom, I was like... "He would fucking hate that."
帶著榮耀之光出去真是太差勁了。
Going out in a Blaze of glory was so fucking lame.
但我們生活在這樣一個社會裡，每個自殺的偉大藝術家都被畫在壁畫上，他們被當作神來談論。
But we live in this society where every great artist who kills themselves is on murals and they're talked about like gods.
-托尼在壁畫上。-是的。這是……在鎮上，就有幾個。
- Tony's on murals. - Yeah. That's... Around town, there are a couple of them.
我該去塗鴉了。
I should go deface them.
如果我這麼做，他會很高興的。
He would love it if I did that.
我收到了你的書面邀請
□ I got your written invitation □
□一根漂亮的棍子打在□的眼裡
□ a beautiful stick in the eye □
我明白了
□ I get the message □
你一直在發送
□ you been sending □
□說再見□是沒有用的
□ ain't no good in goodbye □
□扔掉一切□
□ throw everything away □
任何東西都可以被取代
□ anything can be replaced □
□遍體鱗傷是我唯一能做到的…□
□ black and blue is the best I can do... □
哦。
Ooh.
是的。
Yeah.
□想嗎?□
□ Want to? □
哦，多麼痛苦的asp
□ Oh, what a pain in the asp □
□無盡的愛與奉獻
□ endless love and devotion □
□印度過去的禮物□
□ Indian gifts of the past □
□只是滄海一粟罷了
□ just another drop on the ocean □
□空了空間，空了心
□ empty space, empty heart □
□哪裡有愛□
□ where the love □
□不再是□了
□ is not anymore □
這樣□□
□ so □
□生活在地獄的邊緣
□ Living in limbo □
□親吻□的腰
□ kisses akimbo □
每一座橋都著火了
□ every single bridge is on fire □
□把我抱在一起?□
□ hold me together? □
沒有可能，從來沒有
□ No way, never □
到期日期已過期
□ due date done expired □
□第二次機會是浪費□
□ second chances are a waste □
□我要屈服，直到我擊垮□
□ I'm gonna bend until I break □
遍體鱗傷是我能做到的最好
□ black and blue is the best I can do □
是的，青一塊紫一塊碎成兩半
□ yeah, black and blue and broken in two □
□喔，喔□
□ whoa, whoa □
□想?□
□ want to? □